[music]
Heat.
Heat. [music]
>> [music]
[music]
>> Hello, good evening, good day everybody
and welcome back to the Ask Kabid show
today we discuss anything that you want.
I'll take questions from the super chat
and we will discuss all topics and
before we do that let us see who all is
there with us present in this live
stream who all is there in the live chat
I can see lots of people saw me from
Jaipur hello Mahita Bushetti hello Isaac
Newton good morning brave robot hello
Chatanya Manuja Djamat random skull
hello Vikas PJ Auror Singh Abijit Chava
light [laughter]
uh brave robot once again all right Al
Janib Sri Ramachandraaya Namaha Har
Mahadev Anishh Bharata Namaste Vidi
Manar thank you ma'am vss namaste real
painter tar sar salutations sar indeed
geopolitical dub is here from indor
always good to see you sir aditani
sanut mnay singh once again vs 2400
Abhinav Capil I evolu Isaac Newton once
again keedar praedar praab Oh, Sudir
Kumar, good evening. Uh, injured soccer
player, good to see you. I hope your
injury is healing. Real painter is here.
Mosar, miss you. Real painter, critical
thinker is also here with us. Um, who
else do we have? Injured soccer player.
Yes. Yes, we Nabita Das, good to see
you. Um, who else? Mlevin is here. Brave
robot, Vikas, PJ, Abin of Mishra is also
here. Agni
Agni Agni Vana is here from Kolkata. Uh
Gajapati Dave hello Red John Dak 19
1894. Uh Pratik Vora hello.
Who else? Uh Mlven is here. Sushut
is here from Sweden. Hedge. It's not
hedge. It's hey. I know. [laughter]
Sager Dadani is also here. Vikash PJ. Um
Rudra Gulba. Hello. Dragon 123 Slayer.
Hello Mahushetti Omni Mam Shagar. Hello
Rishab Dang. Uh Guten Guten evening I
suppose Shri D is here from Pune. Abi
Chandel Sagani once again Shub 1405 Jr.
Yes Ara
Brahare happy Sunday to you. Nirvana
Nirvana Shanks Kohi I'm doing great. How
are you doing? Um
uh Manisha Kardosu namaste good to see
you ma'am. And who else? Starfinger is
here. Bush runner is also here. Um
Nirvana Shanks yes Ankita Kachab good
evening ma'am. Anime Bharata good to see
you. Rik 18 8722.
Washt goautami and realir Putin. Hello
and everyone else. Uh Amit Pande is
here. Good to see you sir. Amit Pande G
Ana Malai is also here. Namaste.
Mountain man is here. Thank you sir.
Mountain man G. Uh hish
hers h har h har h har h har h har h har
h har h har h har h harsharidas h har h
har h har h har h har h har h har h har
h har h har haridas ainta Anand hello
sunil
go to me and everyone else okay okay
okay I won't um continue that too long
otherwise it'll go on forever so let's
get going with the questions karthartik
Pand g from LinkedIn hello so what
questions do we have let's discuss all
the topics that you would like me to
talk about let's see what's the First uh
topic that we have WBR says is Trump
good for India considering his actions
have damaged US arms lobby in India.
Certain persons who appeared on your
show was copying was coping certain
person who appeared on my show. Somebody
who appeared on my show was coping in
his 12 May tweet saying Trump just gave
every anti-American in India a whole
load of ammunition. I'm wondering who is
that person who came on my show who is
coping in the 12th May tweet.
I can think of a few people. Okay,
whoever that was. I have had a lot of
people on my show. I've done a 100
podcast episodes thus far and many
people have come. So I'm not sure who
that is. I may have some guesses but
okay. So is Trump good for India? Well
Trump is he good for India considering
everything that he has done? the central
you know there's so much that we can
discuss when it comes to Trump and visav
the US India relationship right but
think about what happened in May we had
the 3-day 4-day war between India and
Pakistan operation zindur and Trump took
Pakistan's side in that right he
essentially came in in India's way he
came and stopped India from continuing
the military operation he he did that he
put he applied pressure on India and we
had to stop. Imagine if India had
continued the air strikes for another 24
hours. None of the Pakistani air bases
would have survived. Not a single
Pakistani aircraft would have been able
to take off
and if it had continued for 48 hours
it's possible that parts of P would have
returned to India.
So Trump stopped. He forced India to
stop because he's because the US is the
most powerful nation in the world. you
know if they apply pressure we've got to
respect the amount of power the US has
so we stopped and ever since that
happened the US has become further and
further pro Pakistan
they are supplying um F-16 spare parts
they may be replacing some F-16s that we
destroyed um the the Trump business
empire is investing billions in Pakistan
in the oil and gas se sector in the
cryptocurrency sector in the rare earth
minerals sector right and Trump has
imposed has gone against like has
imposed massive tariffs on India 50%
tariffs
and he claims that it's because India
imports Russian oil well China imports
way more Russian oil than India the san
and and the tariffs on China are way
lower the US imports uranium from Russia
isn't the US supporting the Russian war
effort so it's just hypocrisy utter
hypocrisy See the objective is to
contain India. The objective is to
ensure that India doesn't grow because
they are worried that India may end up
eventually in the next 20 or so years
becoming the next China. So Trump is not
good for India. Trump is terrible for
India. He's he may be good for his
nation. That's that's a different
conversation whether he's good or bad
for his nation. But he is terrible for
India. The US has never applied this
much pressure on India since before
1971.
So the India US relationship is at its
lowest point since the 1971 war between
India and Pakistan in which we created
this art this nation of Bangladesh.
Yeah. So Trump is terrible for India.
That's the answer. Ritik Pawar says, "Do
you think ISI CIA could be responsible
for the killing of a Bangladeshi student
leader in order to blame India and
intensify anti-India sentiment?" Look, I
I can't speculate.
Some Bangladeshi individual who was
advocating that Bangladesh should invade
India's far east, India's northeast and
you know do that sort of thing.
Virulently anti-India individual. He
apparently
has well lost his life in some kind of
uh un unnatural manner
and because of that the US embassy in
Bangladesh has put out a big tweet
condoling the death of this person and
various European nations have also
condoned you know uh
sent condolences to the people of
Bangladesh about for for the death of
this individual very strange
and it seems it's clearly part of a
concerted
effort, concerted plan to support these
anti-India elements in Bangladesh. Now
whether so and so organization or so and
so agency could be behind it, I can't
say. I can't I don't want to speculate.
You don't ever speculate if you're a
responsible person in the absence of any
evidence. So I can't say.
Of course, it's not beyond the realm of
possibility that so and so agency
organization could potentially perhaps
be behind it. There's always a non-zero
probability of such things. But do we
have any evidence about uh that supports
that? No, we don't. So, I would not want
to speculate about it. Right? But the
it's true that the killing of this
individual, it has definitely
intensified to some extent the
anti-India sentiment in Bangladesh which
was already being fueled by this new
regime, the Muhammad Yinus regime that
has been you know placed in power as a
replacement for Shik Hazina's government
which was ousted in an undemocratic
coup.
So ever since that coup happened in
Bangladesh the entire
um orientation of Bangladesh as a nation
has become more and more anti-India
and this incident will definitely
intensify that to a certain extent for
sure. So yeah,
critical thinker says your three book
reading wisdoms is self-help self worth
it book reading wisdoms.
Uh I'm not sure what you mean by that.
Do you mean how to read books? Uh what's
my approach towards book towards reading
books? First of all um I read whatever I
I find interesting and I don't read what
I find boring or or uninteresting. If
you ask me whether I have readily taper
I haven't read any of her books
cuz I don't find her interesting as a
person as a historian as an intellectual
as a writer I don't find her interesting
she's a propagandist she may be
intelligent whatever so my point is
don't read what you don't find
interesting read what you find
interesting secondly if you are reading
a book and it's not giving you the value
that you seek then stop reading it you
don't have to read an entire a book in
its entirety read whatever you find
interesting Maybe you find chapter 7
interesting. Maybe that's the topic you
find interesting. Then read that and
look around in other parts of the book
whether it's some something there
something that gives you value or
something that evokes your interest.
Otherwise, don't read the entire book.
Thirdly, uh give yourself permission to
forget. You don't have to remember
everything you read. It's okay to to
forget 90% of what you read but that if
you give yourself the permission to
forget then it will ensure that you will
remember what is actually interesting
from your perspective what gives what
you find valuable from your perspective
and that is obviously what will enrich
your life
each individual is different what what I
may find a certain amount of value in a
in a specific book you may find a
different kind of value in that book or
maybe you may find no value at all so
lee Let your curiosity and your
interests lead you and give yourself the
permission to forget. You don't have to
memorize everything. That way you will
re retain what is the most valuable to
you. So that's what I would say. Is
self-help worth it? Well, it depends.
Once again,
some books may be worth it. Some you
know a lot of these self-help books,
they can be condensed down into a
five-page article,
but because the the author wants to
write a book, they expand it and put all
kinds of examples and stories and god
knows what what else in there. And that
significantly dilutes the message.
No, I've in when I was much younger, I
did read a lot of self-help books and I
honestly I'm not sure what value I got
out of out of those. So, yeah, not from
my from my perspective. I think
self-help hasn't really helped me, but u
you know, maybe other people may find
some some something or something of
value in there. So, it depends on on
where you stand in life and what your
objectives are and what value you seek
seek in a book. Critical thinker says
thoughts on Robert Green's book why they
controversial. Robert Green has written
multiple books. There's a book on
war. There's a book on strategy. I think
there's a book on mastery. There's a
book on seduction. I haven't read all
the books. Uh I'm sure I've read the
book on war. Probably the book on
strategy as well. Uh pretty well-written
books.
And those books are about
various principles. So each chapter is
kind of a standalone thing. You can read
one chapter in its entirety and you
don't have to read the rest of the book
because one chapter will most likely
give you uh a specific
strategy, actionable strategy, etc.
They're pretty good books. Yeah, they
Robert Green has distilled centuries of
wisdom into various principles
and uh yeah, I would say the books are
definitely worth reading. Yeah, I
haven't read all of them. I haven't read
the book on what seduction. I haven't
read the book on I'm sure there's a
couple of books I haven't read and I
haven't read any of his books in one
single sitting in one single go in you
know like 3day stretch or whatever. I've
spaced it out over like months and
years. Uh why the controversial because
they deal with controversial topics.
that deal with the book on what is it
strategy the book on war whichever it is
it's about pretty amoral topics you know
the strategies um the tactics that he
speaks about writes about they are kind
of amoral
you can use them for good purposes you
could use them for tremendously evil
purposes if you if you wish to so that's
why there there could be some
controversy behind that Okay.
Says misinterpretation of rigid by
Griffin about beef. I haven't read
Griffin's translation.
And the thing about all these western
translators is that they're going to
insert their interpretations and their
biases into their translations. No two
western translations of the rivida will
be exactly identical.
they will differ and they'll differ not
only in the language but also sometimes
in the meaning in the interpretation.
So I am not sure about Griffin and what
he has written about beef in the riga
but I can assure you that there is no um
section in the rigida that says he
should eat beef. Absolutely not.
Okay. Agni Vana says how tough
engineering and medical terms taught
using Sanskrit. I have no idea.
I I don't know.
Could you teach engineering and medical
um topics in Sanskrit? You absolutely
could. Will it be tough? Well, if you
know Sanskrit, then it won't be tough.
And Sanskrit essentially is all for all
of us. It's the original mother tongue.
Whatever language you speak, if you are
Indian, whatever language you speak,
east, west, north, south, there is a
tremendous amount of Sanskrit vocabulary
that's embedded in our languages,
right? So, Sanskrit is actually a very
easy language to learn if you're Indian,
but it takes a bit of time and a bit of
effort and most people are scared. They
think Sanskrit is some super
complicated, high, incredibly
intellectual language. It's a language
that people used to speak in daily life
a few thousand years ago. And if your
ancestors could speak it, you can also
speak it. And I
I suspect that, you know, engineering
terms and medical terms, they could
actually be way more precise in
Sanskrit. But nobody's attempted to do
this. Nobody has attempted to write an
engineering book in Sanskrit. Would be
really interesting if somebody did that.
I I expect that it'll be way more
precise than in the English language.
Aniket says
scholars scholars say that this chariot
is not a horse chariot because
apparently the wheels are too heavy. Are
they right?
How do we know the wheels are too heavy?
I I I see I know that a lot of these
so-called scholars they call it a a cart
a bullock cart or something
and the thing is if you look at the the
construction the design of the sonali
chariot you will see that the chassis
and other parts of the super structure
so to say of the of the chariot are made
of copper tubes.
Now have you ever seen a bullock cart
whose superructure whose chassis is made
of copper tubes? You won't see that. But
what is it in today's world that is made
of metal tubes?
Formula 1 cars.
So the engineering principles that are
used in Formula 1 cars and race cars
were used in this object that has been
discovered in Zali.
Now if you wanted to make a bulock cart
you would make it out of wood mostly
right? You would need very little metal.
Maybe the axel, maybe a little bit of
metallic elements, but the chassis, the
superructure, you could make it out of
out of wood. Why make it out of copper?
Copper is way more expensive than wood.
You have to go and dig up the ore. You
have to process the ore. You have to
smelt the metal. You have to purify it.
It's it's it's an expensive process. Why
make a bulock cart out of
copper? The superructure out of copper
and why tubes?
Why not just rods? Because tubes can be
shaped into
specific shapes. Rods typically have
right angles etc. So the the design
principles that are used in Formula 1
cars were used in this object and still
people want to call it a bulock cart and
they are making all kinds of excuses.
Maybe the wheels are too heavy, maybe
something else, blah blah blah blah.
There's no evidence it is a chariot,
maybe it's a cart.
So it's the same kind of agenda that
people like Romeila Taper etc. have.
They want to misinterpret everything and
they want to deny
any engineering talent or whatever. It's
all you know it's all mundane objects.
There's nothing special about this.
That's what they want to say. So let's
disregard these scholars and let let us
not waste our mind space by thinking
about what these idiots and these
propagandists are peddling.
Anik says Aniket who makes the world his
home. Okay. Says a lady crafted on a
silver dish which is from the first
century. AD BC first century. Okay.
found in Lampsakus, Turkey, which is
claimed as the as a as the oldest
evidence of Bhat Mata. Is it true? I
don't know. Let's see what Let's find
out. Let's uh try and search this on
Google.
Um Lamp Lamps.
What is Lumpsus? Okay, it's a Greek
city. What's a Greek city doing in
Turkey? [laughter]
What is a Greek city doing in in Turkey?
Turkey was Greece. Okay. Uh, silver
dish.
What is that? Ancient Greek artist
engrave bat mata. Let us see. Let us see
what's the image like.
Well, well, well, well, well, well,
well. That is fascinating.
Byzantine silver plate personification
of India. Sixth seventh century lumps
across Chennakale.
Very interesting.
um lamsacus treasure x.com
is it the personification of India is it
the person personification of bharat
mata
and I have another
tweet over [snorts] here let's see
uh this is a tweet from Istanbul Turkier
on the 17th of January 2022 the account
is called the Byzantine legacy Byzantine
Silver plate with the personification of
India. Question mark. 6th 7th century.
Lamsakos Lamshaki Charakal. Oh, it's in
the Galipoli region. Okay. At Istanbul
Archaeological Museum. Photos taken
today. Let's see.
Good god.
Okay.
Very interesting.
Uh the lady seems to be wearing
something that looks like a sari. That's
the kind of dress she is wearing. She's
wearing sandals. She's got multiple
animals around her. She's wearing some
kind of a crown. She's holding a bow in
her left hand. And we have uh what looks
like attendant attendants who have who
seem to be one with a tiger, one with a
leopard. And there's a dog on the right.
There's a parrot on the left. There's a
partridge kind of bird on the right hand
side. really interesting
and this account the Byzantine legacy
which is definitely not an Indian
account is is wondering whether this is
the personification of India. Now let us
see what my friend Sund Balakrishna has
to write about this. The Dharma Dispatch
is his publication. He's one of our
great scholars. Sundep Balakrishna an
ancient Greek artist engraves Barat
Matau in Lamsa. A thrilling story
narrating the little known history of
how how a Greek artist of the 2nd
century CE ad whatever had engraved in
our image of Parat Matana in Lamsacos,
Turkey. In 1847, a bunch of farmers
digging in a village near Lamshaki
accidentally unearthed a horde of
treasure that proved invaluable to
archaeology. The finding opened several
fresh vistas in the reconstruction of
the history of the ancient world,
especially that of the Byzantine period.
It's variously known as the Lamsakos
Horde or Lamsakos treasure. It's split
across the British Museum, the Louv and
the Eastern Bul Archaeological Museum.
Okay. Lamshaki is a forgotten town in
the Chanakal province. Uh let's pause
this uh Chakal that's Galipoli region.
But in the ancient world, it was a
flourishing Greek colony etc. Okay. For
centuries, wonderful. Lamakos was the of
Priapus, [laughter]
the Greek god of vegetables.
Priapus. Priapus. Okay. Um I should not
tell you why I'm laughing. [laughter]
Okay. Um next
lamakus was also fabled for its
silverware and and so on. And one of the
objects in this discovery was a large
silver dish plate depicting bhat mata as
visualized by a Greek artist who
engraved it on the plate in the first or
second century CE. It is inbul. Now
here's what it looks like. It was uh
okay the Titanic scholar Shivasu Deva
Sharon Agarwal who identified it as Bard
Mata in 14 in 1943
uh and so on. It's a long article so we
will not read the entire thing but it's
spectacular.
It's definitely really interesting. I
was not aware of this artifact. So
Aniket thank you for for bringing this
to my attention. I certainly will uh
look deeper into this. I shall read the
entire article. do my own research in my
own way and yeah this is really
interesting this is something that
definitely merits more attention so
thank you for bringing this to all of
our attention to all of us just not just
me but also the viewers who are watching
and will watch later thank you so much I
will check it out in more detail later
onxg
lolhaha says were the Vikings superior
than medieval Europeans so when we talk
about superior. Let's say we are talking
about the superiority of two phones.
How do we determine which phone is
superior? For example,
do we talk about what the kind what kind
of processor the two phones processors
the two phones have? What's the speed of
each proc processor? How much RAM each
each phone has? What kind of
architecture you know microprocessor
artic architecture each phone is? What
kind of operating system it has? overall
what's the kind of performance you know
under you know when it's it's consuming
more computing power does it get heated
up so we have different kinds of metrics
that we use to determine which of the
phones is superior now when we're
talking about cultures
Viking culture versus let's say uh the
other rest of Europe
if you want to determine which culture
or which race let's say is superior
We need to determine what are we talking
about? What is our definition of
superiority? Are we talking about
military excellence? Are we talking
about wealth? Are we talking about depth
and richness of culture?
What are we talking about?
So, if you ask me if the Vikings were
militarily superior to the medieval
Europeans between so and so century to
so and so century, then I would have
been able to give you a definitive
answer, yes or no. But when you say
superior, I'm not sure what do you mean
by superior? You mean they were bigger,
taller, stronger, more muscular? Is that
what you mean? Do you mean the kind of
wealth they had? The kind of military
technology they had overall, how good
they were from military perspective? If
you talking about just military
perspective, then from the 8th century,
7th or 8th century AD to the let's say
11th century, middle of the 10th
century, the Vikings ruled Western
Europe. They had overrun multiple times
what is now the UK.
Eventually they even settled in
northwestern France. They were
militarily way superior to the Europeans
who lived in these regions. [snorts]
They even served as mercenaries in the
Byzantine Empire and they eventually
founded to to some extent Russia. So
yeah in in from a military perspective
they were definitely superior.
where in northern and western Europe
lol haha says why does Spain's golden
age start when Jews leave Spain look
it's not like that actually
Spain's golden age started when they
started plundering
the Americas
that's where their golden age started
okay but since you are talking about the
expulsion of the Sepharic Jews. That's
something that happened in the uh in the
aftermath of the Reconista.
The Reconista
was a long process of the expulsion of
the Moors from Spain. The Moors were
North African
Muslims who were ruling Spain, who ruled
Spain for a few centuries.
and and and Spain eventually after
several centuries of fighting the Moors
eventually in 1492
in 1492 or 1498 1492 I think it's in
1492 that the Spaniards finally
completely expelled the Moors from Spain
and
that is the year that Christopher
Columbus
discovered
the Americas when he when he was
actually looking for India so that's
where the golden age starts. It has
nothing to do with the expulsion of
Jews. It is it has everything to do with
the expulsion of the Moors who were
occupying Spain for several centuries
and also it has a lot to do with the
Columbus discovering let's say America
and then the Spaniards plundering so
much wealth and gold from the Americas
and of course uh at the end of Donista
the Spaniards decided to also expel the
Jews the Sephardic Jews.
So it all happened essentially around
the same time. But the golden age was a
age of plunder. When you steal so much
wealth from helpless, helpless people,
your golden age will happen, right?
That's how it goes. So let's not
conflate multiple things that may not be
correlated.
UMXG
LHA says Singapore fixed corruption. Why
can't the Modi government do it? Okay.
See, we have to understand that
Singapore is a city state. It's one
city.
Okay. And if you want to reform one
city, it's super easy to do. I don't
think it's super easy. It's still a
herculean task,
but it's way easier to reform one city
as opposed to reforming a
subcontinentsized nation.
Okay.
So it it's it's
it can you can make it sound extremely
simplistic. Singapore could do it. Why
can't we do it?
The Chinese used to the the Chinese
under then shopping used to send
officials to Singapore to study the kind
of reforms Singapore had enacted had had
implemented over the preceding two three
decades.
And the Singapore Singaporean government
was very happy to explain to the Chinese
how did they did things and the Chinese
wanted to learn from the Singaporeans
and implement those measures and those
reforms
and policies in China. And Deng Shaing
used to say I think he said to Lee Kuan
Yu he said that I wish then Shopping
said to Leewanu I wish that I had a city
to reform then I would just implement
what you did and it would be it'll it'll
work out fine. If I had to do this just
in Shanghai, let's say, I would be as
successful as you. But I have this vast
nation
to reform
and implementing your policies
is going to be way different when imply
when when when applied to China as
opposed to applying that that in a city
state. So you know it's very easy to
just make a comparison Singapore versus
India. Both are sovereign nations
technically. Singapore technically is a
sovereign nation. But it it's it's like
it's like comparing um a union territory
like like Du or Dhan with Uttar Pradesh.
You can't compare the two. So please
understand it's it's it's vastly
different. I'm not saying that
corruption has should not be fixed. I am
a vocal critic of corruption. I have
said multiple times that corruption is
one of the major issues that is holding
India back. Something needs to be done.
No question about it. About the alleged
corruption that allegedly exists in you
know various aspects of
the country.
UMXG lol haha says 5 minutes after birth
they they decide your name religion
nationality and sect and you spend the
rest of your life defending what you did
not choose
thoughts it is what it is such is life
such is life what are my thoughts my
thoughts is that these are the real
realities of life if you want to do
something about it if you want to choose
a different name a Different religion,
different nationality, different sect,
it's your choice.
But most people don't do that. The point
is there is a lot in our lives that we
can't control. A lot that has to do with
our life has been decided, predecided
before we even became properly
conscious.
You can't change your ethnicity. You
can't change the color of your skin, the
color of your eyes, the color of your
hair. You can't change your genetics.
There's a lot you can't change. All of
that was determined by your ancestors
whose names you don't even remember or
know. Right? So, a lot in our lives is
determined by factors beyond our
control. My thoughts are that stop
crying about it.
You can't keep crying about I wish this
had happened. I wish that had happened.
I wish I wasn't born here. I wish I had
a different color of skin. and I wish I
had a different religion, whatever. I
had a different name. Forget about all
those things. You are given a certain
amount of time in this life. You don't
know how much time you have. What you
can do is make the best use of the time
that you have and decide what you want
to do. You want to change your name,
change your name. Change if you want to
change your religion, change it. You
want to bleach your skin, it's like some
people do, do it. It's your choice. No
one's going to stop you.
But there's no point crying about things
that you know we can't control. Those
are my thoughts in in brief. Interesting
thought though.
Parthonon says China, India, Russia
can't replace US as the global hegemonic
superpower. As of today, neither China
nor Russia nor India can replace the US.
Even if you combine the hard power of
China plus Russia plus India, we still
three of us combined cannot replace the
US as a global hegemonic superpower.
That is the current situation. I do not
disagree with you at all. You are
absolutely correct.
But how will the future proceed?
How will the world evolve? How will the
global balance of power evolve? It will
determine it will it will be determined
by the actions that the nations which is
the leadership of each nation takes in
the next 20 30 years.
By 2050 you may have a different balance
of power. By 2075 the whole world order
may may have changed. It's possible. So
a lot will be determined by what happens
in the next 20 years. But as of today,
none of these three nations, even the
three of them combined, cannot replace
the US as the hgemonic superpower.
UXG Lolah says, "Thoughts on the
lynching of a
Hindu man uh by um yeah, individuals in
Bangladesh.
Absolutely abominable, absolutely
condemnable, absolutely horrific. I
would say shame on the government of
Bangladesh, shame on the police of
Bangladesh, shame on the people of
Bangladesh that they are doing this to
their own citizens because of their
religion because they are Hindus.
And this is happening because the new
government in Bangladesh, the the
Muhammad Yunus regime is anti-Hindu and
anti-India
and they are emboldened by the fact that
they have a superpower standing behind
them.
Right? So there is this policy right now
that the US has of containing India
using
proxies such as the terrorist regime of
Pakistan and this wannabe
new Pakistan, East Pakistan, Bangladesh
and other factors as well. So that's why
all of this is happening
and it's absolutely horrible,
condemnable and those who are behind
this, those who are responsible for this
need to be brought to justice. That's
what I would say.
Um Lolha says, "Review and thoughts on
Durand?" So I watched Durand.
Uh what are my thoughts on the movie?
Great movie.
It's it's like a 3 and 1/2 hour long
movie and I did not find the movie
dragging at all. The three and a half
hours was actually enjoyable. Typically
when you have a movie that's that that
long you may get bored at some point in
time but it wasn't boring right second
thing there are many of these chase
sequences car chases and all so in a lot
of these fantastic Bollywood action
movies where you have car changes and
all you will find that there is no
continuity between one scene and the
next in one scene three cars are you
know three cars are racing down a
highway next scene when you cut to the
next scene they're going on on a
different road. Next scene it was not
three. It was three cars. Now it's five
cars. Where did the five cars come from?
In the next scene, the previous scene
the cars are going in this direction.
Next scene they're going in this that
direction. There is no continuity. There
is no causal chain between these these
these different scenes. Right? So in
Durand that is not the case. See a chase
scene, a chase sequence is supposed to
draw you in, pull you in. It's supposed
to be gripping. But in so many of these
stupid Bollywood movies, you have to use
suspension of disbelief to to just keep
watching. And that's not the case with
Durand. That's great. Uh the
performances are fantastic. Of course,
very mature performances. Um
Aka Kana is obviously fantastic. Even
Ranir Singh is is excellent.
I I kind of found that that love angle
kind of tedious a little bit. I you need
there are certain portions of that that
need a little bit of suspension of
disbelief. So that's that's just minor
criticism. Some more minor criticism is
that you know when you there's this
scene in which there's a big crowd and
they are firing weapons into the sky and
you can see the muzzle flashes
but the sound doesn't match with the
muzzle flashes. the the bangs, you know,
the the the gunfire reports don't line
up audio visually with the muzzle
flashes at times. There are some minor
quibbles, but overall it's a fantastic
movie. Uh it doesn't follow a three-act
structure, which is interesting. In case
you know about writing,
fiction writing, etc. You know,
typically a movie, a book, it follows a
three-act structure. In the first act,
you introduce the world. You do some
world building. You introduce the main
character, the main antagonists and you
introduce the problem that has to be
solved by the main character. In the
second act, the problems pile up, pile
up, pile up and you know it becomes
really difficult for the for the main
character to you know to do to achieve
what what they want to achieve. And in
the final act third act there is a
resolution at the end climax. That's a
three-act structure typically in fiction
whether it's movies or books. But in
this movie, you have chapterization and
it's based on real events and the names
of characters have been slightly changed
but you know exactly who they represent
in the real world. That's great. So it's
kind of a fictional documentary based on
real world real world um incidents and
uh it's kind of a groundbreaking. See,
if you want to if you want to break new
ground in cinema,
if you want to break new ground in
cinema, you have to do what other what
previous filmmakers have either been
scared to do or they have chosen not to
do. You have to do something new that
has not been done before. That's how you
break new ground in cinema or any field.
So in this movie, this movie has broken
new ground. They have shown the truth
about Pakistan. They have shown the
truth about the Pakistani terrorism
aimed at India. The it's it's by no
means an anti-Islam anti-Muslim movie.
It just shows the truth about how
religion in Pakistan is used um in
conjunction with the anti-India
terrorism.
It also shows the complexity when it
comes to Balojasthan.
See we in India have this black and
white vision of Balojasthan. Balojasthan
is is a victim of Pakistan but the movie
shows that a lot of Baloce are involved
in terrorist activities against India
right it also shows in one scene that
the Balois are being oppressed by the
ISI by the Pakistani regime etc. So it
shows complexity.
The world is complicated. It's messy.
But Indian cinema has typically treated
the audience as children, black and
white like that. So there is no spoon
feeding. There's a little bit of
spoonful spoon feeding when the when the
when the Hamza character opens his his
his diary or notebook and does this
invisible ink thing and write down
writes down names of people and then
crosses a name out. That's kind of spoon
feeding. That's kind of, you know, if
you want to treat your audience as
grown-ups and intelligent people, you
don't need that. You don't need the love
angle. So, I have some small minor
criticisms, but overall a great movie. A
movie that definitely breaks new ground
in in the perspective of Indian cinema.
Uh yeah, I I enjoyed it. I would
definitely recommend everybody watches
it. It's definitely a groundbreaking
movie in the context of Indian cinema.
And I suppose even non-Indians would
enjoy watching it. Yeah. Even though
it's a three and a half hour long movie.
So overall, if I had to give it a rating
out of 10, I would give it a nine.
There is always room for improvement.
I would actually give it maybe 7.5. But
because it is such a groundbreaking
movie for India, because it has shown
the truth about Pakistan, it has not
been afraid to do what other other
filmmakers have been afraid to do
because of all the things. Instead of
7.5, I will give it a nine. And I hope
that the next chapter which comes out
next year is going to be even better. So
overall, I really enjoyed it. I would
like to congratulate what's his name of
the um his name is Ashish Dar, right?
um the director the the the maker of the
movie tremendous job outstanding job I
am a big cannoner of of of films
I know what is good cinema this is not
just good but great cinema really
enjoyable so yeah overall that's my
review of the movie
lol haha says why is the quality of life
in Indian cities so bad worse than
Southeast Asia
look one one word okay not two
We start with alleged that's the first
word. Second word is corruption. Alleged
corruption. Alleged corruption.
I'm sure there are certain Indian cities
where there is none of that. And there
must be some Indian cities where you
have tremendous terrific quality of
life. There are certain Indian cities
where the quality of life is way better
than than certain very large cities.
But the root cause of most of the
problems in India is the alleged
corruption. All right.
Uh El Janib says, "How to reconcile
nothing?" How to reconcile nothing? Big
bang singularity. You see
nothing which is the big bang
singularity created something valid
within confined reality. Example, the
first law of thermodynamics in a local
universe and relativity inside
space spacetime fabric.
See the big bang singularity was not
nothing.
We don't know if it was actually a
singularity or whether it was a very
small something.
According to le according to LQG loop
quantum gravity it was not an actual
singularity.
It had a finite volume 10 - 97 um meters
cubic meters that that sort of thing if
I'm not mistaken if I recall correctly.
Um, so the entire mass energy of the
universe was confined in that very tiny
volume. So that's not nothing. That's a
lot of stuff in a very small volume.
That's an incredibly mindboggling
density of matter energy.
And if it was a singularity and maybe
look quantum gravity isn't the correct
theory. We don't know if it is, right?
So if if it was actually a singularity,
then you still had something. A
singularity is not nothing. A
singularity is a is an infinity. An
infinity is a lot of stuff, right?
So um first of all that and secondly so
how did it create something valid within
confined reality? It's the first law of
ther thermodynamics. So the first law of
thermodynamics is what does it say? It
says that it's a it's the law of the
cons law of conservation of energy.
Energy cannot be created. Energy cannot
be destroyed. Energy can simply be
transformed from one form, converted
from one form into into another form.
That's the first law of thermodynamics
made as simple as possible.
Um so yeah that's what we observe in the
universe. Right? So first of all we have
to understand that the even if the big
bang the start time t equal to0 state of
the universe was a singularity even that
even then that singularity was not
nothing. It was everything confined into
well
a one-dimensional point essentially. See
we can't really physically define the
singularity. The best we know see how
did we come up with the big bang theory.
We observe the universe. We see all
this. We collect all the data. We see
that the universe is cold. It's getting
colder. It's expanding. Spacetime is
expanding and everything is getting
further and further away. So all you
have to do is to run the clock backwards
and then the you see that in the past
everything would have been much closer
together and the universe would have
been much smaller and denser.
And the logical conclusion is that is
that at time t equal to0 you had
something similar to either a
singularity or a very very very very
small universe. [snorts] So we don't
quite know. See the physics of the very
early universe is not well understood at
all. We are not quite sure how the how
the universe was and what the physics
was like before inflation.
So you know so it's very speculative.
The physics of the very early universe
is very very poorly understood and
that's an issue but that's a great issue
to have. [laughter]
So that's the point. So so the question
that you're asking it it assumes that
there was nothing in the beginning which
is not the case. All right.
>> [snorts]
>> UMXG lol haha says thoughts of the book
which of us are arians by the renowned
respected magnificent madame rula tapar
many Indians trust her because of her
educational background
so I haven't read the respected
magnificent Madame Romeula Taparj's
great book which of us are audience I
haven't read the book but I am aware of
her magnificent work. I'm aware of her
magn magnificent work. Let me give you
an example of Madame Rila Tapar's
magnificent work. Okay, let us go to
Google.
Let me give you an example of her of the
magnificence of Rmula G's work. Okay, so
Bodana
Sutra. What is the Bodhyana Sutra? So,
let's go to what Wikipedia has to say
about this. As always, Wikipedia is not
a reliable source of information
necessarily, especially when it comes to
Indian history. Now, the Bodhi Short
Sutra is a late Vic text uh within the
whatever. Okay, it's uh Krishna
Yajurveda that was composed in eastern
Uttar Pradesh during the late Brahmana
period. What is the late Brahmana
period? What is this nonsense that
Wikipedia you know vomits out at us?
Anyhow, the Bodhi Yana Shot Sutra is
it's a late Vic text. Now,
and it's about [laughter]
what what's it say? What's it say?
Translation controversy. Okay. So,
according to Michael Videl, this this
fascinating gentleman, um it points to
Indo-arian migrations um migrations, his
translation says blah blah blah. It says
that au it was Amawasu right not Aayu
Amawasu they have changed it see
Wikipedia anybody can change so Amawasu
went eastwards that's how we translated
is people are the kurup panchar and
kashi vidha this is the migration blah
blah blah and
they have changed this article let's
change let's see the history and let's
go back to an earlier time when um okay
okay okay so let's go to the maybe 2017
version of the article. Okay. So
um
what does it say? So where so even here
it says that okay so historians like so
based on Vitzell's article Roila Tapper
stated that this passage contained
literary evidence for Arian migration
and so on. And the problem with this
translation is that the text actually
speaks of a westward migration.
Okay? Not an eastward migration.
So the point is that Rmula Taper has
tried to misinterpret
the text, mistransate the text. She has
supported Michael Widzel in his
distortion of the text. And this is
something that Rmula Taparj the
magnificent historian is known to do.
She is part of the colonial school of
Indian history. The euroentric colonial
hindophobic school of Indian history.
That's what she's part of. So you see my
problem is that I have self-respect.
Now what what do I mean by I have
self-respect? It means that I respect my
time. That's that's one example of
self-respect. I respect my time. I am
acutely aware that each each individual
all of us each of us has a limited
amount of time in this world and I want
to maximize the value I get out of my
time and the value I create from my
time. So how do I maximize the value I
get from the time that I have? By
reading good stuff by not wasting my
time reading
garbage. And which is why I have not
sadly regrettably read any of Madame
Ramula Taper Gi's magnificent works. I
haven't I have read some of her
articles, research papers as part of my
research that I did when I wrote before
I wrote the my my my article on the uh
Arian invasion myth in 2016 2017
whenever it was I did read some of her
work at the time. uh but I haven't read
this book so I don't have any thoughts
in the book but I have very clear
thoughts about the magnificence of
Ramula Taparji she's part of the
magnificent
colonial euroentric hindu phobic
literary historical school of historical
analysis and that's why I haven't
bothered to read her books but I have
seen excerpts of her books see before I
move on to the next question I I have
strong opinions about historians
whose works I haven't read properly.
Right? Why is it so? Because I'm aware
of the pattern of the patterns and I
have read excerpts of what they have
written. And that if you read the
correct excerpts, the right focused
excerpts then you don't have to read the
entire book. One paragraph will give you
a great idea if you if you focus on the
right paragraph. For example, in the
past when it comes to our greatest and
most magnificent prime minister Sri
Jabahal Nehuji,
I haven't read his fascinating book, the
discovery of India
and I have
probably offered some criticisms
of the book. Now I have seen some
comments on my on this channel saying
that if you haven't read the book then
how can you criticize it and say it's
garbage.
It's because I know
some of the stuff that's written there.
I have read excerpts. I have read
passages. Sometimes one sentence
or one paragraph gives you all the
context you need.
Okay? So you don't have to read an
entire book before you have to form an
opinion on the book. Sometimes
one page is enough to tell you exactly
what the book is about. Sometimes just a
paragraph is enough to to tell you
exactly what the book is about. Let me
let me show you an example.
Okay. Okay. Uh, Java
L Jabar Lu discovery
of India
South Indian temples.
What did he say?
Um,
check this out.
BJP claims. No, no, no, no, no. It's not
BJP claims.
Where's the excerpt? Where's the
excerpt?
I can show you an excerpt.
Uh
where is the excerpt? Um
is this a speech from Mr. Neu? So this
is an example. Some of the temples of
the south however repel me in spite of
their beauty. I just can't stand them
stand them. Why? I don't know. I can't
explain that. But they are oppressive.
They suppress my spirit. They do not
allow allow me to rise. They keep me
down. They're dark corridors. I like the
sun and air, not dark corridors and so
on. So once you
once you read some of the excerpts from
a book or and so on, you get a good idea
of what the person is all about, then
there's no need to read further, right?
So yeah.
Struggler says, "What should India
actually do about Bangladesh? Why didn't
we vaselize it? Well, why didn't we do
first of all after 1971, we should have
simply reinccorporated Bangladesh back
into India. We had conquered Bangladesh.
We had liberated Bangladesh from the
parasitical West Pakistanis
who had been conducting a genocide while
the rest of the world including the
superpower United States averted their
eyes.
Right? So we liberated Bangladesh from
the parasitical genocidal West
Pakistanis.
Our armed forces were all across
Bangladesh. We had taken Dhaka. We had
taken the rest of the country. Why
didn't we simply reinccorporate that
country back into India? From 1947 to
1971. How many years is that? It's what
27 years.
20 24 years. It's 24 years.
It had been out of India for only 24
years. Why didn't we simply
reinccorporate it back into India? Huge.
huge mistake then there would not have
been the kind of radicalization that's
happened over the years over the decades
and which has brought us to the current
situation in Bangladesh that would not
have happened so why didn't we do it I
can't I can't answer the question only
the leadership of the time can answer
the question and that leadership is no
longer with us so I can't say what
should we do about Bangladesh well
that's a great question
what should we do about Bangladesh
um right now there's not much we can
Because Bangladesh is supported by the
United States just like Pakistan is. If
we take any military action against
Bangladesh, the the world will label us
as a wararmongering country and hit us
with all kinds of sanctions. So that is
what they actually want us to do to take
military action so that they can
sanction the hell out hell out of India
and destroy India's and crush India's
economy. Right now what India will have
to do
is
what India needs to do right now will
have to do right now is simply ensure
that the borders are secure and the
armed forces are vigilant so that
there's no more infiltration or
terrorist activity that comes out of
Bangladesh and just ignore Bangladesh.
They'll keep on poking and proddding us
and issue keep on issuing inflammatory
statements etc about us. keep our calm,
ignore it
and and rise. India needs to grow
economically and militarily the next 20
years. We just need to ignore all these
barking dogs etc. I don't mean to be
derogatory to the people of Bangladesh.
I mean the current Bangladeshi regime.
Okay, there are many great people in
Bangladesh. There are many people in
Bangladesh who are great f friends of
India.
I'm not saying all Bangladeshies are
anti-India. Many of them are not. But
the current Bangladeshi dictatorial
regime is virulently anti-India.
That's why I say that Bangladesh has
become East Pakistan again. So what we
need to do is ensure border security.
Ensure there's no more illegal
infiltration out of Bangladesh.
Repatriate and deport all the illegal
Bangladeshi infiltrators who are in
India. Each and every one of them, every
last one of them. And then seal the
borders for the next 20 years. And India
needs to grow economically and
militarily. Once we are a 1015 trillion
dollar economy,
none of these nations and none of these
matters will be much of an issue for us
and then we will be able to well take
actions that would be suitable for those
times. That's what we need to do.
VSVS namaste G namaste. Good to see you
and thank you so much.
UMXG lol haha says why do coins have
ridges around their edges in Europe now
okay now you are giving uh you had asked
this question yesterday about why do
coins have ridges and I gave you many
examples of coins that don't have ridges
if you look at ancient Indian
numismatics coins don't have ridges but
in Europe
coins apparently have ridges why is that
well it is possibly because you know see
coins historically
in the past used to be made of precious
metals, silver, gold, etc. And there
were some unscrupulous people, citizens
of various nations, kingdoms, etc. who
would clip the coins. So if you have a
coin of this size, they will clip a
small small amount of the gold out and
they will accumulate the gold clippings.
And if you clip enough coins, you have
you can acquire a substantial amount of
gold over time slowly slowly slowly.
Sometimes they would clip substantial
amounts of lot of coins. So that's why
that's why uh ridges were introduced on
coins
so that if uh in and essentially it
would be that anybody who gave you a
coin
with a clip which had a clipping mark
and the ridges were damaged then you
could hold the person liable for for
theft. Uh
that that that was the idea and that's
why ridges were introduced around coins.
UMXG lolhaha says Rabbi Mizachi
a renowned Rabbi says
go/imps are not acceptable and dawned
to live I have no idea sir I I have no
idea
vindi manar says what is most what is
likely to come for bat in a few months
now
what's
likely to come for bat in a few months.
Let's talk about 2026. What's likely to
come? More pressure from the US,
more economic pressure, maybe the
tariffs will continue, maybe heavier
tariffs,
uh more provocations from East as well
as West Pakistan,
u possibly
pressure from China.
So, it's not going to be an easy time
the next 5 years for Bharat. I expect a
war with Pakistan in the next couple of
years and the earlier it happens for
India the better it is perhaps.
Uh so it's going to be a tough time for
us the next 5 years in the next 20 years
also. Uh it's possible that you may have
another conflict with Pakistan in the in
the next few months. It's possible. Uh
we're going to be have to be very
careful about China also because they
are increasing their their force posture
ne north of the Indo Tibet border. So
yeah, we're going to have to be very
alert and it's going to be a difficult
time ahead for India. But that's how you
achieve what you have to achieve. Life
is not all all flowers. It's sometimes
guns as well as roses.
Okay. James, my friend James says the
great western world researches with
proofs. Brahi is from Semitic.
Who is a small YouTuber to say that it
isn't? We research with knowledge not
garbage.
[laughter]
Right? So, Wikipedia, what does
Wikipedia have to say about the Brahi
script? The Brahi is a script. It's not
a language. FYI for everyone. Uh, Brahi
script.
The Brahmy script, it's a writing system
from ancient India. Okay. Uh, what does
what does the AI Google AI say about the
origin? Brahm script origin is debated
pointing to either an ind indigenous
evolution from the industript or a
foreign derivation often linked to
semmitic scripts like Aramaic and
Phoenician potentially introduced during
the aid Persian period. Um yeah
so the Google so this this is an AI
overview by the Google AI most likely
Gemini if I'm not mistaken and
historically
if you if you look at older textbooks
even current textbooks written by
foreigners or Indians they will say that
the brah script was derived from um from
from either Aramaic or Phoenician and
Aramaic and Phoenician are derived from
Egyptian hieroglyphics so that's the
mainstream view even today.
But
if you see the older versions of the
brahi script, you can see more and more
similarities with the Sarasati Hindu
script.
So actually [laughter] if you have half
a brain, you can see how the brahi
symbols the symbols of the brahi script
they evolved from the older Saraspati
synd.
So that's what actually has happened.
But if you are a person who who uh ised
by authority and eminence and not by
logic. So there are various kinds of
people in the world. The more
intelligent ones like the ones who watch
this channel, they will understand that
you have to look at the world from a
logical perspective. Even if a great
eminent person says something, you still
have to examine the logic skeptically.
You have to be skeptical about all
claims and you have to validate all
claims based on logic and first
principles no matter where the claim
come from came from even it even if it
came from let's say a Nobel prize
winner.
Okay. For example, Albert Einstein was
of the opinion that black holes simply
cannot form. He even wrote a published a
paper saying that black holes simply
cannot form. Black holes can't exist. He
published a paper claiming black holes
cannot exist
despite his own equations
demonstrating that a black hole will
form under specific circumstances. Carl
Schwarz was the first person to to solve
Einstein's field equations and something
frightening was was embedded in the
solution and Einstein was he didn't like
it. It made him very uncomfortable. And
the same year that Einstein published
this paper saying that black holes can
can never form. Oppenheimer and Snder
published a paper showing black holes
will form. But the world took note of
Einstein's paper and and Oppenheimer who
was still not famous. His paper got
buried. Oppenheimer and Snder.
So the world tends to be overed
by authority and eminence. So most
Indians are even more like that because
you know the education system conditions
us to just worship authority and bow
down to authority and if somebody
eminent says something that has to be
the gospel truth. But if you are capable
of critical thinking you will know that
every claim has to be examined logically
and from first principles. And if you
examine the question of the origin of
the brahi script from from the
perspective of logic and first
principles, it makes no sense to claim
that it has come out of
you know it has it has descended
from either Aramaic or Phoenician makes
no sense. You you can see clear onetoone
correspondence between Brahi characters
and Sarasati Hindus script characters
and you can see actually how the
characters evolved. So I am glad that
James has brought this topic up for
discussion. I really appreciate you
James as always. Thank you very much.
Vsvs says question by Isaac Newton. Sir
Isaac, good to have you. Um, China has
developed an ASML machine which is a
massive feat. Well, it's under
development. It's a it's it's not a feta
compli. It's not done. It's not the
final product yet. They are trying to
develop such a machine a photo
lithography machine
and which company is the well the
preeeminent manufacturer of photo
lithography machines it's ASML the Dutch
company what is a photoiththography
machine ultraviolet um you know it use
ultraviolet rays it is a machine and a
photoiththography machine is a machine
that
manufactures
that that
manufactures chips. So you have a
silicon wafer but you want to create a
microchip based on the silicon wafer and
a microchip is incredibly
der it's it's like you know the the most
basic components of microchips are
smaller than viruses.
There's a tremendous amount of circuitry
let's say that's embedded in in a tiny
microchip. How do you do that? You do
that using photoiththography machines.
So if you want to become au
a worldclass semic semiconductor
manufacturer chip manufacturer you need
a machine like that.
You need photoiththography machines at
the kind of with the kind of
sophistication that ASML has. And China
is trying to do that. they have you know
ASML they employed Chinese origin
engineers and the Chinese have let's say
acquired those engineers some of them
and they are helping China man you know
develop such a machine so that's where
China is China is trying to catch up in
everything
they are trying to catch up with the
west in every single technology they
want to be completely self-sufficient in
everything
They there are Chinese companies that
are trying to uh develop reusable rocket
technology, self-landing boosters, the
kind of boosters that that Space X has
and they are making decent progress in
that. What about ISRO? Absolutely
nothing. So where is India when it comes
to photo lithography machines? Is India
too far ahead or will India start to
accelerate as cities like doera queen
city and gift start to grow? I hope so.
I am not sure what is the status
when it comes to photoiththography
technology in India. Is India trying to
develop such technology? I am not quite
sure where we stand right now and it
doesn't look like
look we we are making decent progress in
in this field.
Um recently some some new chip was
developed indigenously. So we are making
decent progress but if you want to be at
the the worldass level the cutting edge
of technology if you want to be a major
participant and major player in the AI
race for which you need very powerful
chips well in that case we will have to
try and develop our own photo
lithography machines and I'm not sure
where we stand in that. That's my honest
answer right now.
AJ Sharma says I'm 25 with a German
passport Serbian v wife. Okay. Your wife
is Serbin. OCI.
Okay. Or um overseas citizen of India.
Okay. So, full west mobility and a
system to fund above average western
European life by the mid30s with blocks
and CBDC's best hedge nomad or one
country roots. Let me just check out
what is a CBDC. I obviously have heard
of the term but I can't remember what
that is. CBDC.
What's a CBDC? Okay. Central bank
digital currency.
Okay. Okay.
So, you're 25. You have a German
passport. You are Serbian via wife. You
have OCI card. So, full east west
mobility. Um, you have a system to fund
above average Western European life of
the mid30s. Okay. So, you're kind of set
in life. That's great. That's great.
Congratulations. Now, with blocks and
central bank digital currencies, what's
the best hedge? nomad or one country
roots. Look, I would say that you need
to have ideally as many options as
possible.
Um,
I mean, ideally, [laughter] look,
ideally, you want to have a home in each
continent. Let's say, you want to have a
home in Australia, you want to have one
in the EU region, maybe a couple of
homes in the EU region, one in North
America, one in South America, one in
India, let's say, one in Japan. Japan
doesn't work but maybe New Zealand. So
ideally that's what you want. You want
to maximize your options and that
obviously is a kind of a nomadic life. I
would say it depends on what appeals to
you in life. If you have the system that
will ensure that you have an above
average western European life and
sufficient funds by your mid-30s,
then
either if if travel appeals to you, if
mobility appeals to you, then I would
say go for a semi-nomadic life. Maybe 6
months of the year in one country in the
and 6 months in two three countries. But
what's the best hedge from a security
perspective? That's what you're actually
asking.
Look, I am of the opinion that Europe is
declining. And my opinion is based on
what I'm seeing on the data and the
facts, right? Europe is declining. The
quality of life in Europe is declining.
There's the illegal immigration issue.
Uh the European economy economies aren't
doing well. So Europe is not a long-term
bet. 20 years from today, Europe is will
not be the same thing, same entity, the
same quality of life that that it is
today. Certain parts of Europe will
still be great. London is the world's
moneyaundering and financial capital.
London will still be great, but London
has become Londonistan.
So
considering that maybe having options
would be good for you. So if if you are
if you are doing if you're happy with
living in Germany, you can live in
Germany, but always have the option to
to be able to move around if you know if
and when things kind of go south. Uh
yeah, so if you have multiple passports,
etc., etc., it helps. If you have a
passport that opens multiple doors, lots
of doors, it helps. Um that's what I can
say. So what I what I see is that Europe
is declining and the quality of life in
Europe will decline. So based on that
you need to you know
create the right options. All right sir
all the best sir do well. Do well.
Bijuya says there are no gay or lesbian
chromosomes. Then how are LGBTQ people
born? Is this really a biological
condition or a mental condition? I am
not. I am I have not done any research
into um
this matter. I don't quite know. Look, I
do not even I was not even aware of the
existence of homosexuality until I was
what
maybe 18 199. [laughter] I had no idea
that this even existed.
So um and look it's it's not something
that uh I have I have nothing against
LGBTQ people etc. My point is I've never
been never found the topic interesting.
I've never done any research into it. So
is it a biological condition? Is it a
mental condition? I what is the origin
of specific orientations?
I don't quite know. I don't quite know.
Yeah. So I [laughter] I sadly don't have
an answer to your question, sir. Sorry.
Um Ritik says, "How did Bakty Kilji meet
his death?" I believe he was it. So
Bakty Kilji is the barbarian who
destroyed Nalanda and did a lot of
murdering and rampaging and genociding
in various parts of India and it is if
I'm not mistaken he tried to do the same
thing in Tibet and he met his end over
there. So I think he died in Tibet he
and his skin he was his body was
apparently skinned and his skin is still
kept somewhere apparently in some
Tibetan monastery or something. Let's
let's quickly Google this. Yeah.
Bakti Kil Kilg Muhammad Bakti Kilg
uh how did Bakti Kilji died? What sort
of grammar is that? Die. Okay. How how
did how did Okay. How did this
individual how did Bakti Ariel Gi die?
Died from illness and injury. That's
what Google says. after his disastrous
Tibet campaign also is reportedly
assassinated by a rival while in DV
court after devastating retreat from
Tibet means defeat in Tibet. he died.
Um,
so that's what Google says. I haven't
really looked into this this
individual's death. Uh, death in
aftermath.
Okay. In Dave quote after defeated by
Tibetans, he was assassinated by Ali
Mardan Kilji, whoever the hell that
individual is. So yeah, this is what
Wikipedia says. That's also what what
what Google's AI says.
I had also heard that he was killed in
Tibet and his skin was kept in the
monastery. Maybe that's just an urban
legend or something. So yeah.
Uh VSB says VSBS says James James should
[clears throat] marry Rana Aub to make
Abhijit Ayar Mitrai angry. Okay. I I
hope James James is watching and maybe
he can do that. Right. [laughter] Okay.
Uh, Bijua says, Bijua says, you sit down
and talk for hours. Does that give you
any pain or any other problem on mouth?
No.
I see.
Look, I'm not actually much of a talker.
I'm not, which will be very strange to
those of you who are watching. That will
sound very strange to you because I talk
for hours. Uh, I have over definitely
over a thousand hours of me talking on
YouTube, right? Uh typically one of
these live sessions it's about two maybe
3 hours. Yeah I've done some very long
sessions. I did once the longest session
I did was almost 9 hours long. The next
day I just kept quiet. I was worried my
throat will go go down south but it
didn't didn't happen. So um speaking for
2 or 3 hours doesn't really give you any
pain. I mean I don't feel any physical
pain back pain or whatever that people
worry about. I don't feel any pain uh in
any part of the body and mouth. No.
[laughter]
You know, we all know people who talk
all day, right? There are people who
will speak from morning till night. Does
it give them any pain or create any
health issues? No, nothing. So, speaking
for two or three hours is not really a
health hazard. And sitting for 3 hours,
I have even sat multiple times for 8
hours. I mean, I've done that live.
as long as you take care of your body
and you you do the right exercises and
workouts and and so on, you'll be able
to handle that. So, you have to take the
uh right precautions and if you do that,
you're going to be perfectly fine with
no issues whatsoever.
Gabati says the US wants a naval base on
St. Martin's Island in Bangladesh.
Yasina refused and was replaced with
Muhammad Yunos. Is the US turning
Bangladesh into a Ukraine for India by
supporting the anti-Hindu movement
forcing us to take military action? So
yeah, there have been reports that the
US wants that naval base wants St.
Martins's island to create let's let's
find let's locate this island. We
haven't opened the map yet. So let's
open the map and let us locate this
island.
So we are talking about the Indian
subcontinent. We talking about
Bangladesh
and where is this island? So it is this
most likely this tiny island here, St.
Martins's Island. Let's take a look at
the U satellite imagery on the map. Do
we see any new interesting activity
here? I'm not sure how old these images
are. It's possible that these may not
have been uh updated in recent times,
but thus far it doesn't look like there
is any
any
military activity as such on this
island. I can see I noticed something
here.
Helipad. Okay, these are helipads. So, I
don't see any new construction happening
here. But yeah, the US is definitely
interested in this in this island
because with the right kind of uh you
know restructuring, a little bit of
restructuring, you can create a a proper
air force and naval base on this island.
It's not a very large island. Let's see
the dimensions from north to from south
to north. It's about four almost 5 km.
So you can definitely construct a proper
like 4 kilometer air runway on the
island and uh with some land reclamation
etc. you can make a proper military base
on the island maybe an air base plus
naval base you certainly could do that.
So that's why the US is interested in
the island. I'm not sure if they have
taken possession of the island or not
but yeah um and it's not just because
they want the island and shakers in a
refuge. That's why they they ousted her.
Not not quite. They want to contain
India from both sides. It's not just
east and west Pakistan. This entire
cookie land issue
that the terrorism in Manipur all of
that that's also linked
connected with this objective of
encircling India.
They want the creation of an artificial
new nation called cookie land for Christ
out of parts of Burma, parts of Manipur,
parts parts of India, parts of um
Bangladesh. Now that Bangladesh is on
their side, they don't need to take
Bangladeshi territory. But they want to
create a de facto
artificial nation whether it is
recognized by other nations or not. They
want to create a big territory where you
have a cookie land for Christ in parts
of Manipur. They want part of they want
to incorporate that into that to to to
infringe on the sovereignty of India and
create problems for India in the far
east of India. So all of this is all
interconnected. The the issue in
Manipur, it's not a civil war where one
Manipur ethnic group is fighting another
Manipur ethnic group. It's not that.
It's foreigners occupying Indian
territory. That's the issue.
So the main question you're asking is is
the US trying to create turn Bangladesh
into Ukraine for India and force India
to take military action. Well, it's our
choice whether we take military action
or not. Every problem doesn't need a
military solution. There are all kinds
of solutions, creative solutions that
are available to us at our disposal. We
will not take military action. There are
other ways of dealing with things. There
are very creative ways of dealing with
various issues.
It's not only our enemies who know how
to play those games. We also can play
every game in the book. Right? So yeah,
you will see anti-Hindu activities in
Bangladesh. For sure. The Hindus of
Bangladesh are now again facing the same
days that they had possibly uh in the
run-up to 1971. Hopefully that's not the
case. Hopefully that's not the case. But
there is definitely more hostility
towards Hindus and you know we see
what's happening. But uh we will not
allow Bangladesh to be turned into a
Ukraine. That's for sure.
Biju Sika says why Europeans, Japanese,
Koreans are not able to reverse their
TFR downfall. Will India face the same
problem after a few decades?
Will India face the same problem? See
right now what is the current TFR of
China? What's the current TFR of China
of of Korea and Japan? It's it's
dreadful. Let's see. Uh, South Korea TFR
2025. What is it? Ah,
so South Korea's TFR is 0.65 in 2023.
Good gods.
South Korea's fertility rate 0.65.
to to sustain a population at the
current level,
you need a TFR of 2.1, which means each
w each woman should on average give
birth to 2.1 children. Okay? On average,
it's not like every woman will give
birth to 2.1 children. On average, the
number will be 2.1. That's what you need
for the population to remain at the
current level. If it goes below 2.1, the
population will eventually start
declining. the population will start
declining in South Korea it's 0.65 65
which is which is which is disaster
which is disaster which means the
population will start declining there
will be way more deaths than births and
the average age of the population the
median age will start increasing what is
China's TFR let's see
China TFR
1.3 that's again disaster level what is
Japan
Japan TFR 2025 2020 25 sorry
1.38. Ah ma'am okay let's see uh EU
what's the EU's DFR 1.4 once again it's
terrible
significantly below the 2.1 replacement
level what about India it's 2.0 I think
right oh 1.9 to 2.0 Z. So we are also
going down the same road.
So when you have a TFR of less than if
it is less than 1.5 you are talking
about demographic disaster
and then you can maintain population
levels only through immigration which is
what the EU is doing to itself.
Now India our population is very high
1.4 plus billion. So a lot of people are
in favor of a one child policy etc. But
have you seen what happened to China as
a consequence of the one child policy?
China's what is China's median age
today? Let's see
median age. China's median age is today
40.1 years. What about India?
It's 28 29. Okay. So China median age
what will it be in 2050?
50 to 54 years old. The average person
in China will be over 50 50 years old in
2050 which is horrible. You want your
the average person to be young. What
about Japan?
Japan is going to beif 50. Yeah,
similar.
Uh what about E India? Let's see. It's
going to be in the 40 38 39. So that's
bad. So our demographic dividend that we
talk about it's the next 20 years after
which our population will be older and
older and older if the TFR decline
continues. So India will face the same
problem if we don't correct the TFR. See
the ideal population of the Indian
subcontinent should be about 350 million
maximum. We are way beyond that. So we
need to bring the population levels
down. But if you bring it down too
rapidly, too drastically, then you're
going to have a demographic disaster
where everybody is old
and very few and when you have an older
and older population, the birth rates
drop even faster, which eventually leads
to extinction.
I'm not joking here. It's not going to
happen tomorrow morning. It's going to
happen in the next 100 years. Do we want
that?
So if India needs to bring down its
population levels to something more
sustainable maybe 500 billion it needs
to happen over the next 10020 years it's
a long-term project right so yeah so why
are Europeans Japanese etc not able to
reverse the TFR downfall
uh see why does TFR go down why do
people have less children
because it becomes too expensive to have
children that's number one and secondly
they are overworked.
If you have to work 12 hours a day, 7
days a week or let's say 10 hours a day,
five, six days a week, then you're going
to be exhausted all the time and you
will not be able to procreate.
Makes sense. I think if both husband and
wife are always exhausted, always
working, never together,
then how will they have children? And if
both are working
then who will take care of a child if it
is born?
If if you need two salaries to to run a
household and then if the child's
education is too expensive
then even if you have one child you will
not want to have another one because you
you won't be able to afford it.
Education is too expensive, healthcare
is too expensive, everything is too
expensive.
the so either you spend a lot of money
to to raise a child or you give the
child a terrible upbringing,
a very unhappy upbringing. Do you want
that? So because of these reasons, TFR
goes down.
The cost of living is very high, in
Japan, in Korea,
in the EU, in China, it's not the case.
But they make they they dug their own
grave with the one child policy,
right? And in India the TFR is now going
down because the cost of living is high
because people are poor because
everybody wants to move to cities and
for for to be able to afford life in a
big city both husband and wife need to
work if they are both working then who
will take care of the children when the
family we no longer have extended
families together all these problems are
going to bring TFR down. So that's these
are the reasons why TFR goes down. India
is going to face the same problem. in
the in maybe in 20 years.
Yeah.
Achinta Anand says various Buddhist gods
are depicted as harming our gods. They
call
Buddhist texts
call Hindus ichantika or non-believers.
um created untouchable cast for animal
bully as only death of ichantikas was
was was allowed and not animals but they
wanted to consume meat. So it's
interesting that Buddhists are allowed
to consume meat as long as they don't
kill animals.
So they have the animals killed by
somebody else
that you will see
you will see it in Bhutan you will see
it in other parts in various Buddhist
regions that Buddhists will eat meat but
they won't kill the animal themselves.
So killing is not allowed but eating of
meat is allowed. I'm not sure how it
works but that's what I've seen myself.
Yeah. Now,
for example, in Bhutan,
you can eat yak meat. The yak is like a
mountain cow, but it's not a cow. It's a
different species of animal. It's part
of the boine animal family, which
includes buffaloos also, right? So, they
will eat cow. They will eat yaks, but
the the yak will be will be slaughtered
by somebody else by by non-buddhists,
maybe by Hindus, whatever. [snorts]
So that's one thing. Now you will find
Buddhist deities trampling Hindu gods
for sure. No no no question about that.
That is just a fact of life. Okay. Let's
see. Buddhist deity is trampling
Hindu gods. The these are these are
facts. Okay. Uh we are not making this
up. Uh subject trampled deities under
trampled figures underfoot.
Uh what do we have?
Not sure what that is. Let's see.
There's This website seems to be very
slow. Uh angry Buddhi. No, I'm not
looking at Dave Datnak
Rathpool deities.
Um
so Vajri Yogini
who is she trampling?
Vajger Yogini. Um, let's see. Let's open
the page about Vajger Yogini. And uh,
who is she trampling?
No, it doesn't say anything about
trampling. But you can clearly see she
is trampling two figures. And one of the
figures looks
does is it Lord Shiva? I'm not sure who
is the other figure. It is obviously a
female figure. I'm not sure who Vajrain
is trampling but the point is that you
will find Buddhist deities trampling
Hindu gods Buddha Vajarapani trampling
Shiva and Parvati under his under his
feet achal crushing Ganesha under his
feet
um yeah there is there is no question
that this is the case
let's see images
trampled gods and deities page once
again you will see various you could say
Hindu gods being trampled by Buddhist
deities this is definitely a fact nobody
can deny this why is it the case I'm not
sure uh were Hindus called Ichantikas or
non-believers I believe they were Hindus
were called ichantikas non-believers so
yeah
there are uncomfortable facts
in history
and we should be able to discuss this
openly right so there's no question
about the fact that various Buddhist
deities are depicted as trampling Hindu
gods no question about that it it is
true
and uh Buddhists won't eat won't kill
animals but they will eat meat and they
will have where untouchable was an
untouchable cast created for animal
slaughter. I I don't know about that.
That is something we may have to look
into. Uh Hindus were called antaas and
non-believers. I think certain Buddhist
texts say that it is texts I believe
they do say that it is okay to kill
antaas but not animals. Yeah. So there
are these issues. No question about
that. Um yeah. So how did Buddhism
become so widespread? uh Buddhism was a
very fringe obscure
philosophical path of Hindu of of
Dharma, right? It was our emperor Ashok
who his patronage who made Buddhism so
widespread both the dharma across India
and even even beyond India and and it
became a big thing because of Ashoke
because of imperial patronage otherwise
you know Buddhism would have gone the
same path down the same road as
potentially um
certain other like the u what was
There was this
sect of people that Ashoke had
uh
had oppressed, right? Ashoka Ashoka the
great
which
which sect was it? Uh let us see
imperial extent conversion to Buddhism.
Um, Kolinga.
Yeah, I forget the name of the sect, but
uh let us see. Seabard
Ajiv Ajivikas. Yes. Ajivika.
Yeah. So he executed 18,000 followers of
this sect maybe. So today we don't know
much about the Ajivika sect which was
once a thing, right? So Buddhism may
have gone down that the same road if it
was not for imperial patronage from
Ashok
says Usman Hadi was our agent. How dare
raw take him out. How dare they? They've
crossed the line they'll soon regret.
This is no trifling matter. We'll make
them understand the consequences of
their actions. Who is a a Osman Hadi?
Who is that? Let's see. Osman Hadi.
Who's this? This man Hadi
a Bangladeshi politician activist. Is he
the individual who was taken out by
someone recently
uh dece 18th December 2025? He was a
Bangladeshi poet and [laughter]
political activist
and uh he was shot. Oh he was shot.
Tragic tragic. He died on 18th December
while undergoing treatment and there was
nationwide violence.
and so on and he was buried in some
place political career and called for a
national government blah blah blah blah
blah influence on anti-Indian hegemony
Indian hegemony in Bangladesh
so he was an anti-India individual and
James says that he was an agent of the
west well you see sir James I it's you
may be
Even though the west western governments
have not officially
taken responsibility for cultivating
this individual as their agent, it is
possible perhaps even likely that he was
either directly or indirectly by proxy
an agent of the west. It's possible. Now
did RAW take him out? There is no
evidence for that. So I I will
obviously deny I mean I don't represent
RAW. I have no connection with RAW as we
all know but there's no evidence that
connects RAW with his uh tragic demise.
So I would say his demise has been
tragic. Uh human lives are valuable even
though some humans are anti-India which
is okay but human lives do have a value
and it is definitely a tragic tragic
occurrence that he has uh mysteriously
died an unnatural death apparently.
Apparently was shot. Whoever did that I
I condemn. I condemn those people. Yeah,
I also condemn his anti-India actions
also. But yeah, so yeah, that's what I
can say about this. James
uh Polarise says, "What could happen if
we make a CERN like particle collider
and put North Indian polluting particles
in it? Would it blast?"
[laughter] That's a great thought
experiment. So in CERN, you had multiple
particle colliders. Okay. The one that
currently operates in CERN in CERN is
the world's most powerful particle
collider. It's called the large hadron
collider.
Okay?
And it consumes [snorts]
the the amount of electricity that a
small country would consume on an annual
basis. That's how much energy goes into
powering this gigantic uh machine, let's
say.
So let's say we build a large hadron
collider kind of machine in India. When
we put the north Indian polluting
particles in it, what will happen? Will
it explode?
See, it won't work. I'll tell you why.
What you do in something like the LHC is
that you take particle antiparticle
beams
and you spin you know they they they
travel
in the collider in a basically circular
path and they are eventually smashed
together at very close to the speed of
light. And then there are instruments
around the place where the smashup
happens which take pictures of what came
out of the collision debris. Okay. So
when you take particles and you and you
make them fly around at close to the
speed of light to make this happen, you
have to create an almost perfect vacuum
in the circular path where you're going
to have the particles zip around.
So you have to you need a vacuum for
this to happen. Now if you want to put
polluting particles which is polluted
air into the this this machine then the
vacuum is gone and nothing will work. So
the machine only works when there is an
almost perfect vacuum in there and then
the particles which are going to be
smashed together are introduced and spun
around through magnets very powerful
magnets
and that's how it is done. So if you put
if you put polluting so first of all if
you want to put particles the pollution
particles into the this machine you have
to first extract the pollution particles
out of the air. There is no technology
that I know of that can extract
pollution and polluting particles
from air and and and and do that do
that. Yeah. So the only answer is you
take the dirty air and put it inside the
machine. But then the vacuum is gone and
the machine doesn't work anymore. So it
doesn't work. You see VSVS says question
by Abujit Chabda light. How is Russia
more powerful than China when China is a
larger economy and Russia just has more
WMDs.
[snorts] when it comes to hard power.
Okay,
see let's say you have two nations both
have hard power. What are the elements
of hard power? Well, typically it's
economic power and military power.
There's also other elements. You can add
nuclear weapons. So that's part of
military power. Of course, nuclear
weapons, your nuclear capabilities are
part part of your military capabilities.
also the number of people, the size of a
of your uh of your land area, the size
of your population, the amount of power
production capabilities that you have
and and so on and so forth. So when it
comes to the elements of hard power,
first of all, Russia has a much larger
territory than China. Secondly, China
has a much larger population. So that
kind of offsets each other off. China's
economy is way larger than Russia.
Now,
China's military expenditure is way
larger than Russia,
but Russia has way more WMDs, like you
say, nuclear nuclear warheads than
China.
Now, it depends on how you calculate
hard power. What kind of formula you
use, what kind of equation you use to
calculate hard power. At the end of the
day, hard power is a number.
It's a number.
So from based on how I have calculated
hard power the US has a score of 94
point something Russia has a score of
what 54 point something China has a
score of about 18 point something India
has a score of about 4.9 so India is
number four China is number three China
is about
it's about four times more powerful than
India okay
and Russia is about three times more
powerful than China and the US is about
twice as powerful as Russia Now I have I
have given a certain amount of weightage
to nuclear weapons.
Now if you remove the if you change the
weightages then you can assign a
different score. So based on how I see
the world, how I understand the world,
based on my understanding, my experience
or whatever, I have given different
kinds of weightages to different
elements.
And when you have a nation with the
world's largest nuclear arsenal, it's
going to dwarf any economic might any
other nation has because China can't
flatten Russia. Russia can completely
flatten China, right? I mean that itself
will tell you that Russia is more
powerful than China.
China cannot flatten the whole of
Russia. If China let's say
hypothetically launches nuclear strikes
on Russia, Russia will be significantly
damaged. But if Russia has taken the
right precautions of securing its
leadership
and other things then Russia will
survive. But when Russia launches a
retaliation, nothing in China will
survive. Nothing will survive.
So that's why Russia is more powerful.
When you if you were to compare purely
economic might versus purely military
might then if you have a lot of money
without a powerful military and without
powerful nuclear weapons without
sufficient nuclear weapons your money is
useless and worthless. So that's why
China is now trying to augment its
nuclear arsenal. That's what one years.
But as of today if you if you assume
China has 600 nuclear warheads which is
the number that is out in the public
domain. And if you assume that Russia
has 5,500 roughly, then Russia is way
more powerful, way more powerful than
China.
Okay. Sam the Gamer says 1776 English
versus English on stolen native land.
That's what it was. Yes. 1776 is the
year the US acquired its independence
from England, from Britain, right? The
American War of Independence. So it was
English fighting English
for this stolen native land.
That's what it was. No question about
it. And the the Americans, the
independence activists, they were
fighting England because they did not
want they did not want to to pay 2% tax
to the British crown. What is the income
tax today in the US? One of the highest
rates of income tax in the world. Like
25 30 I don't know 35%. I'm not sure
what it is. Maybe even more. Let's let's
find out
uh income
tax
rate
in ah the US.
Let's see
uh progressive
seven tax brackets. So if you are a
super poor person, you pay 10%. If you
earn a decent amount of money over
600,000
a year, you're going to pay 37% tax. So
you're going to but there are ways of
well let's not say evading but for so
today the Americans pay way more tax
than what they went to war for.
All right. Swastik MKkesh Mahesh Swastik
Mahesh says what actions is the
government taking against illegal
immigrants? I don't know. I'm not sure.
Hopefully, we are taking some actions,
but I am not sure what actions the
government of India is taking. Um, this
question can only be answered by the
government of India, not by me. Sorry.
Okay. Tony Ferguson says, "How did the
Kanjats
crush Arab invasions again and again,
stemming the Islamic tide for 200 years?
And why isn't this history taught in
NCERT?" I'm not sure. Who are the
Kikats? Let's find out. See, even I
don't know. There's so much I even I
don't know. Kikhan Jats
Khan Jats the brave jut and med people
people of Khan in Sind Indas region who
famously repelled multiple 7th century
Arab invasion attempts showcasing yeah
AI AI talk showcasing significant
military resistance against invaders
during this era. Kikan Jats the Yeah, we
know who the Jats are.
Okay. Does this this Wikipedia article
say anything about the Kikan Jats?
Jats Jats of Sind blah blah blah western
jatsan
jats jats juts juts juts
it talks about lhana jats but not kan
jats so clearly this is um an aspect of
Indian history that has been suppressed
I myself am not was not aware of the
kikan jats I will look into this but I
I'm not sure about the specific details
of uh what actions that took against the
Arabs. So I'll have to do some reading.
Shashank says, "How are elephants used
in ancient Indian wars? You mean how
were elephants used in ancient Indian
wars?" See, today in today's warfare, in
20th century warfare, okay, you had
multiple elements.
Let's say you let's say you are a nation
that's invading another nation.
Hypothetically, completely
hypothetically, in the 20th century, you
would use what? You would use armored
vehicles, you would use tanks, you would
uh have an air force, you would do all
that. You would have infantry. Um,
so one of the major innovations in 20th
century warfare was a tank. What's a
tank? I I suppose everyone knows what a
tank is, but let's see. A tank.
This is a tank. Why is there shopping
for tanks?
[laughter]
Okay, so this this vehicle is called a
tank, right?
This this here is a tank. It's it's a a
20th century innovation. It is still
used in warfare today.
So elephants were like tanks, almost
indestructible,
and they could wipe out dozens of the
enemy of the adversary soldiers. at a go
in a in a go.
So that's how elephants were typically
used. They were used like tanks like
tanks were used in the 20th century
warfare. So you would have an elephant
with a mahawat who would be guiding the
elephant and giving instructions and you
know essentially driving the vehicle so
to say and you would have soldiers,
archers, lancemen also who would sit
maybe three four people on top of the
elephant and uh they could take out
enemies from a vantage point up up top
and the elephant itself was a weapon.
the elephant would go and trample over
the enemy soldiers and the elephants
would often be armored. So even if the
enemy shot arrows or or used spears
against the elephant, if the elephant
was armored, the elephant could take it
and by the time you can react, the
elephant will would would crush the
adversary soldiers. And elephants were
used for for shock purposes, you know.
So especially when it comes to for
barbar foreign barbarians who were not
familiar with elephants it would the the
very sight of elephants would cause
panic among the foreign soldiers even
even their horses.
Um and if you had a force of let's say
500 thousand elephants you were
essentially invincible.
You were invincible. So that's how
elephants were used in ancient warfare
in India.
MK says, "The longer we wait, the more
powerful Pakistan becomes militarily
through US aid. What should India do?"
Well, India should also take steps to
become more powerful militarily in the
meanwhile until the next war happens.
So, we need to augment our um
our stockpiles of various kinds of
missiles. We need to augment our
anti-aircraft, anti- drone, anti-missile
capabilities in whatever way is
required.
Um
the air force acquisitions will take
time, fighter jets and all that. That's
a slow process. But if you're going to
have a war in the next 6 months or one
year, you need to the war will be won by
the side that has the better missiles
and and more more missiles. So if
Pakistan has 1,000 missiles, but we have
5,000, we're going to win the war. That
sort of thing. So we need to augment our
stockpiles of various kinds of missiles.
Brahmos missiles, scalp missiles, Meteor
missile, scalp missiles, um the the the
the
Dhanush, Tishul, etc.
All the missiles that we have, we need
to have see essentially India needs to
have a stockpile of maybe tens of
thousands of missiles of various kinds.
If we have that, we are essentially
invincible.
Invincible. We need to have like 30, 40,
50,000 missiles in our stockpile. That
way we can see because if you look at
the Ukraine war in a single day several
hundred missiles are used
at times when when the fighting is is at
its peak. See the Ukraine war is more
than 3 years old now but there were
times when there was intense fighting
and those times you you know hundreds of
missiles were used in a single day. So
if you have a hot war that goes on for a
week for example
then you're going to use up several
thousand missiles possibly
and we also have the spectre of China
right the China China issue so that's
why India needs to have a stockpile of
several thousand missiles
so the longer the Pakistanis wait the
more powerful we should also become and
eventually there's going to be something
that triggers the next war
possibly sooner rather than later so
that's what India needs to
I would not go and say that we need to
spark a war inside a war sometime soon.
A war will happen sooner or later. It
will it will happen. But we should
ensure that we also get stronger while
the Pakistanis are getting stronger
because of American aid.
Vssvs, thank you very much, sir. Thank
you.
Ashoto Dar says, "How will three war
start if it happens in 2027?
Whether it happens in 2027 or 2026 or
2032,
a three-fold war is a three-fold war.
Now, what's a three-foot war? When we
talk about India's security
position, let's say in the subcontinent,
what we have in the north is Chinese
occupied territory, Chinese occupied
Tibet and Chinese occupied Singang.
That's what we have in the north.
In the west we have west Pakistan. In
the east we have east Pakistan. Now out
of these nations three nations see the
all three nations east and west Pakistan
and China are anti-India.
Now if there's a war that that involves
all three of the nations east Pakistan,
West Pakistan and China all three of
them against India. How will it start is
the question.
How will it start?
See it will either see Bangladesh is in
no way in no shape or form capable of
fighting a war against India. If it
initiates a war against India it will be
flattened in no time and its geography
will change or it will cease to exist.
Bangladesh is not a military threat to
India. It is a demographic threat to
India. Its military there's nothing they
can do. They can't even dream of a war
against India. They will make big
statements all these half rabid half mad
Bangladeshi politicians and so-called
student activists they will go keep on
you know
unleashing these these statements and
and and fiery speeches and provocative
you know speeches about India but that's
just words on on on the ground level
there's nothing Bangladesh can do to
fight India it'll be flattened in no
time so if a war starts it will either
be started by Pakistan or by China
let's say Xiinping is facing pressure
from home or wherever the economy isn't
doing well. China is being humiliated by
the US. China's uh reputation is is
going down. China's um
you know
China China is not doing well overall.
China's prestige is going down and
there's this talk about Taiwan but
Taiwan is never happening. The US is too
powerful.
the US is able to safeguard Taiwan and
if if China tries to attack Taiwan, Tai,
you know, China will lose. Maybe there's
a situation like that. So in that case,
China may decide that, you know, let's
do a short sharp war against India and
defeat them fast. The Chinese may think
that they will succeed and if the
Chinese and attack India and there's a
war, then the Pakistanis will most
likely take the opportunity to start a
war against India. Maybe the Americans
will instruct them. Okay, this is now
this is when you do the do do it. So a
war between India and China if it lasts
beyond 3 4 days will definitely see chi
see Pakistan getting involved.
If the Pakistanis start a war
and and and and if the if there's a war
between India and China in which
Pakistan also gets gets involved then
Bangladesh may try to play some
mischief. So that's a three-f frontont
scenario
and then India's armed forces will have
to be fight will have to fight on three
fronts which is problematic.
If the Pakistanis start a war which is
more likely then will Bangladesh get
involved? Probably not. They pro
they they they'll lose very badly. It's
only if China and Pakistan are both
fighting India that Bangladesh will
perhaps be tempted to get involved or be
instructed by the Americans to get
involved. So these are the possible
scenarios.
If it happens in 2027 or 26 or 2032,
it's going to be the same kind of
scenario.
NK says, "How come China underwent
communist revolution despite being
relatively more conservative than
Europe?"
It has nothing to do with being
conservative or being liberal or
whatever. Nothing to do with that.
China was [snorts]
see China was under the western boots
for a while. The Chinese
make it a point to keep rebinding the
whole world that there was a century of
humiliation and they teach their
students about the century of
humiliation.
The Chinese the west did not do even
onetenth
to China of what they did to us. But we
don't talk about the that right. So the
Chinese were under very yeah you could
say humiliated by the westerners and the
Chinese empire the emperor became just a
namesake emperor a puppet which is why
other forces emerged in China
non-imperial forces one of them was the
kin tang the other was the Chinese
communist party the Chinese communist
party under maong etc. They believed in
communism. They believed that all this
religion and all it is is bad.
It is it needs to be removed.
So that's how it h and there was a civil
war. China was overrun by by Japan to
some extent in Manuoko Manuko the
eastern front and it was some parts of
China were under Japanese occupation all
that stuff and in the meanwhile there's
a civil war going on. So even so that's
how it happened and then the Chinese
Communist Party succeeded. They were
able to defeat the Ku Tang and expel
them and that's why you have a separate
government in Taiwan. That's the Kuang
the legacy of the Kuintang and the
Chanka.
So it has nothing to do with whether
you're conservative or not. When a
nation lacks leadership, when the
emperor has been reduced to a puppet or
an emperor only in name, when there's a
power vacuum in a nation, that's when
all kinds of and when when the nation is
impoverished,
then people will look for any kind of
solution. And communism is is very
attractive when you are super poor,
right? When you can blame
[clears throat] the rich people and
whoever else. So that that's when a
nation is is down on its knees, when it
is impoverished,
when it's humiliated, sometimes
communism becomes very attractive.
Aljunib says
definitely more than definitely way more
than meets the eye with Trump's
spectacular U-turn in no time during
Operation Synindor. JD Vance referenced
JD Vance statements may be serious
damage to US assets or nukes. So yeah
when operation Sindur starts the first
day the second day JD Vance is like you
know what it's a war far away and it has
nothing to do with us and we will not
interfere and then on day three Trump
says I have called everybody and I have
made a I have ensured this a ceasefire
right spectacular U-turn so something
happened on the third day
that suddenly the Americans decided that
they have to immediately urgently
interfere and put an end to the fighting
Clearly something happened. Now
obviously what happened will not come
out in the public domain anytime soon.
What one can speculate if you want.
It's clear that some F-16s were
destroyed. So the Pakistanis claim that
they destroyed certain Indian air bases.
Look at the American and Chinese
satellite imagery. There's not a scratch
on the Indian air bases but you can
clearly see multiple Pakistani air bases
have taken significant hits significant
damage hangers have been obliterated
Nurh Khan air base and Bolari and
whatnot it's clear it's the hard
evidence is out there and you had
American assets over there American sold
assets to Pakistan like F-16s now when
you have F-16s in Pakistani hands you
have a bunch American babysitters there.
The Americans have sold the machines to
Pakistan,
but the Americans monitor the machines
all the time 24 by7. You wherever
there's an F-16, there's going to be a
bunch of American technicians who will
never let the aircraft out of the out of
their sight, which means the air the
aircraft the Pakistani F-16s operate
only with the permission of the United
States. the Americans won't allow
Pakistan to use the F-16s in a way that
will go against American interests. So
if the Pakistanis want to attack India,
they'll be given a go ahead. So that
sort of thing. So wherever you have
F-16s, you have American personnel
there. So if F-16s were blown up by
missile strikes, it's possible that
American personnel may have been blown
up along with the F-16s.
And so that's one one possibility which
may have urgently required Trump's
intervention. Maybe more personnel will
die and we don't want that to happen
because the American technical personnel
potentially may not be allowed to move
to a different location and leave the
F-16s unsupervised. It's a it's a
possibility. Secondly, the nukes.
Look, I have no evidence when I say this
to back up my claim, but I believe that
the Pakistani nuclear weapons are
actually American nuclear weapons. I
don't think the Pakistani
engineers and scientists had the
wherewithal to develop nuclear weapons
on their own.
I firmly believe that these nuclear
weapons are American nuclear warheads
that have been placed in Pakistan
to counterbalance India.
Now these nuclear warheads will be
stored in secure locations.
Apparently Kirana Hills is one location
where they were stored under under a
hill and uh we did hit that and maybe
the missile that we used was able to
penetrate deep inside and you know take
out a few nuclear warheads. So if
American nuclear warheads are blown up
that becomes a problem. So that also
could be a reason why Trump suddenly
urgently made a U-turn and and
interfered.
Gapati says, "I want to ask a question,
but YouTube super chat censoring it."
I'm sorry to hear that, but YouTube's
algorithm and YouTube's mechanisms are
beyond my control. So I'm sorry about
that. Yeah.
What can I say? What's beyond our
control is beyond our control. YouTube
is YouTube. YouTube will do what it
wants.
Sorry to hear that sir. Sorry. Vsvs says
question by real Vladimir Putin.
According to Chanaka, knowledge gained
from enemies should not
missed.
How would he view Einstein leaving Nazi
Germany because of fear of Nazis?
Um I'm not sure if Tanaki has made said
said such a thing.
A lot of
quotes are are attributed to various
people which may not be connected to
those people. U knowledge gained from en
from enemies should not missed
should not missed.
I'm not sure what that means. Should not
be misused or should not be missed.
Logically what what would I say?
Logically I would say you should learn
even from your enemies. So if your
enemies have something to teach you, you
should learn that. So if your enemies
are really good at something then you
should not so that I will not learn from
my enemies, you should learn it from
them too. So for example, China regards
India as an enemy. China treats India as
an enemy. But there's a lot that India
can learn from China. So we should learn
those things,
right? There's a lot India could
potentially hypothetically even learn
from something like Pakistan. Pakistan
plays geost strategy sometimes better
than India. I mean historically it has
played the game better than India.
Right? Only now India is doing a better
job.
So yeah that that makes sense logically.
Now how would Chanaka view Einstein
leaving Nazi Germany because of fear of
Nazis. China did not care about who did
what. Chanaka was all about national
security, national policy,
state craft, geopolitics
and um international relations.
Chanaka would not care whether Einstein
left Nazi Germany or not. And if he
left, so be it. See, Einstein was not an
engineer. Einstein was a theoretical
physicist.
He did not leave Germany with nuclear
weapon secrets.
Einstein did not know how to build a
nuclear bomb.
He is one of the founding fathers, let's
say, of quantum mechanics.
He and Neils Boore are the two giants
who first set up the foundations of
quantum mechanics. Of course, you have
Max Blank who was the first of them all
and you have Heisenberg and Schodinger
and
many more. But Einstein is one of the
absolute giants. But he did not know how
to build a nuclear weapon.
His theory, his insights were used later
on by
experimental physicists and then by
engineers
right to build nuclear weapons. So China
would not care.
Nahusha Nahusha Acharia says can we
restart book discussion like you did
with North American on North American
colonization look there's only a certain
number of projects I can take up I have
so many interests there are so many
highquality projects that I can work on
but right now what I'm working on is on
writing a number of books and that takes
up more of my time see I have been
speaking over here on YouTube for what 4
years now don't you think it's time for
me to write something
right so I'm focusing on writing down
right now because of that I'm not going
to be doing this book discussions for a
while now the not the understanding
America project is a very high value
highquality project and it is not
terminated it is simply right now paused
I shall restart it but I need to
complete
a certain number of book projects before
I can find the time to do that. I hope
you understand.
It's time for me to actually put out
work in writing. I have obviously I'm
going to continue the the work I'm doing
doing on YouTube. These live sessions
will continue. No question. But that
project is currently on on on hold. It
is not terminated. I am going to resume
the project at at the right time. But I
really appreciate that you liked the
work that I was doing and I will resume
that sooner rather than later hopefully.
VSVS says question by Aush Singh. Isn't
the importance of the silk route
overstated given India's extensive
independent trade network with Europe.
How did the term silk route originate?
How significant was it?
Look, the major trade was between India
and the west. When I say west, it is
everything west of India. India was
doing a lot of trade with West Asia,
with Mesopotamia. India was doing trade
with Egypt. India was doing trade with
Rome. India had connections with Greece.
India was doing trade with Africa. India
was even doing trade with Suburanumi
that is Southeast Asia. It was India
that was doing the trade. But western
see I was talking about this yesterday
there is there has been this concerted
long-term project in the west to deny
the Indian and Hindu origins of
everything. So they have created this
this fantasy of a silk route silk road
or whatever. The Chinese were a great
trading nation and they traded with
Europe. I'm sure there were some
caravans that passed between China and
Central Asia and on the way to Europe,
but the quantum the volume of trade that
happened between India and the West, it
dwarfed the volume of trade that
happened between China and the West. And
when the Chinese were trading with let's
say the West
you they often had to pass through
Indian middlemen. One of the major
Indian middlemen of the t of a certain
time was our great emperor Kanishka who
was squarely between China and and the
west because he had conquered
significant portions of what is today
China including Tibet including
Shinjang. He had conquered territories
all the way to the shores of the Caspian
and Aral seas.
So a huge territory in central Asia in
Shinjang and Tibet and much of northern
and western India including the coastal
regions of Gujarat where you had major
ports. So when the Chinese potentially
would have wanted to trade with the west
they would have had to pass through
Indian territory kaneshka's territory
and kaneshka made sure he would tax them
to the fullest.
Right?
So this term silk road silk root it's
all European like see the Europeans have
done so much damage to the world by
creating these these myths one myth they
have created is the South China Sea it
was never Chinese
the so-called South China Sea was the
Champa
the kingdom of Champa a greatocratic
kingdom dominated this region for close
to 1500 years there was no Chinese
presence in the so-called South China
Sea. But the Europeans decided to name
it the South China Sea, which is why the
Chinese are claiming it today. The
Europeans have done so much damage to
the world. They've they've created all
these distortions of history, which is
why all these fake narratives
rule the roots today. So we are taught
there was a there was a silk road. The
Chinese were great a great trading
nation and there was no Indian presence
at all north of the Himalayas. That's
what we are told. That's what we are
taught which is a complete lie.
So the silk root and we had some
Europeans who ventured into China like
Marco Polo and that becomes the the
basis of all these myths you know so it
all originates with Europeans
who sought to distort history
okay MK says what's my review of Dundra
movie at the beginning I I described in
detail what my thoughts were overall a
great movie yeah
so I won't take this question mult
multiple times in this in this live
stream only once uh when the live stream
ends you can check it out I have spoken
about durand and overall great movie I'm
very happy I was very happy to watch it
very interesting did not bore me three
and a half hour movie doesn't bore me
must be really good right and and pretty
groundbreaking very good movie I would
highly recommend it obviously it's not
for the faint of heart because there are
some scenes that are pretty what's the
term graphic whatever that means it's
not for everyone you know So
vidu vinod
vinod ringaraj says visited bookf fair
more
tr less Indian
a book fair you had audrik's books there
yeah
that lady ah
like
a rabid hindu phobe that lady
an outright
unvarnished enemy of India and Indian
civilization. Sad.
Uh Amisha says views on Durand and Duv
destroyed this movie. Who duv? You mean
Duv? Rati.
That's a distasteful name to take.
Who is he?
He destroyed this movie. [laughter]
Yeah, I suppose he must have said
something or other. Did he make a video
about it? I don't watch his channel. I
don't follow him on social media. So I
have no idea what he has said or not. I
suppose he if he has spoken about it, he
would have been very critical of it.
Obviously naturally
my views on Durand are is that are that
it's an excellent movie.
I was see I broke my own rule of not
watching Hindi cinema and I went and
watched it uh last week sometime.
I watched an 8:00 a.m. show cuz I don't
have time throughout the day. So, I went
early and watched an 8:00 a.m. show and
I was very pleased, very happy with the
movie. Uh, overall outstanding,
something Bollywood has never done
before. Groundbreaking movie and I
highly recommend it to everybody who who
can take some violence because there are
some scenes that are pretty violent and
there's blood and so on. So, if you can
take it, do watch it. I I was very
pleased to see it and then I will
definitely watch the sequel. I believe
they've said that the sequel will come
out sometime next year, March, April,
something something like that. Whenever
it does come out, I will definitely
watch it. I was very happy to see the
performance of all the actors. All of
them performed great.
Um, yeah, overall definitely an
outstanding movie
and I will recommend it to everybody.
VSVS says, "Sam the gamer. He um can you
ask sir 40 rupees super chat to write a
history book of India? It is definitely
on my to-do list but see right now I'm
working on a couple of book projects.
Many of you will know what I'm working
on but there is one book project that I
have not spoken about and I will not
speak about it until it's done. So see
writing a book takes time takes several
months.
The writing process once your research
is done let's say you are an expert in a
topic okay then you don't have to do a
lot of research then you can just go and
write the writing process takes about if
you're writing let's say thousand words
a day
maybe the writing process will take
maybe 3 months yeah then once the
writing is done you have to cool off for
a couple of months and forget about that
book after so that is the first draft
that is not the final version. So you
write the book let's say in 3 months
then you take two or 3 months off when
you don't look at the what you've
written at all that gives you a cooling
off period in your in which your mind
has kind of forgotten about the book.
Then you go and go through the entire
book again and then you will find lots
of defects in the book. Then you go and
create a second draft.
Then you may do a third draft also. So
it's a long process
and typically well most people will be
happy if they write one book a year. I
am giving myself a more ambitious target
of more than one book a year and I have
so many books that actually exist inside
of my head. They all need to come out
before the time I'm done. So yeah
definitely thank you for the
recommendation.
Uh Gapati says YouTube super chat
censoring me asked question in regular
chat. Please see. I am only looking at
super chats right now. I want to There
are like about 2,000 regular chats. I
will not be able to find it.
I won't be able to find it. I'm sorry.
I'm I'm really sorry, but if I start
looking at the regular chat, it will
take me half an hour to find it. There
are so I can see the number of regular
charts right now. About 2,000. How will
I find your comment in those 2,000?
Won't be possible, sir. Very sorry. Very
sorry. I really apologize but it's it's
it's
not going to be possible right now.
Hyphen says if the earth's rotation
speed gradually slows down over the next
10 years what will happen versus if it
suddenly slows down tomorrow.
Um
the earth's rotation the angular
speed of earth it is slowing down.
Uh see the earth was the earth formed
about 4.5 billion years before today.
That's 45 with eight zeros after it.
That's many that's how many years ago it
formed. And when the earth was young
let's say about four roughly 4 billion
years old. One day was about 10 years
maybe 4 and a half billion years before
today or maybe 4 billion. But in during
the youth the in the young age of the
earth one day was about 10 hours which
means one rotation full rotation took
about 10 hours. Today it takes about 24
hours. So in about roughly 4 billion
years it's more than
it slowed down more than it's the the
the
it's become more than twice as long.
Right. the the the period of the day two
and a half times roughly as as as long.
So the rotation speed has slowed down
significantly. So that's already
happening.
Now over the next 10 years also over the
next 10 years also the rotation speed
will slow down just very very minutely
very fractionally we won't be able to
notice it. But what if it slows down
maybe 10%
for whatever reason? What will happen?
What will happen is that u uh the day
will become longer.
When you have such a significant abrupt
slowing down of the speed of rotation,
the day will will become longer. The the
earth moon system will be thrown out of
phase possibly because the earth and the
moon are tidily locked. uh you always
see the same face of the moon because it
takes the moon see the for the earth to
rotate once fully it takes 24 hours for
the moon it takes about 28 days which is
why we always see the same face of the
moon always
so if the earth's rotation suddenly
slows down in just 10 years then the
earth moon system will be thrown out of
phase and you will be able to see other
other parts of the moon also um it may
affect tides it may affect all kinds of
things it will affect circadian in
cycles of people
you you will suddenly no longer be able
to sleep properly. You'll wake up at the
wrong time, go to sleep at the wrong
time. All kinds of issues will happen.
So it's obviously unnatural. It won't
happen like this naturally. And if it
suddenly slows down tomorrow, well, if
it suddenly abruptly slows down, then
you'll have a tremendous amount of
sloing of the oceans, massive tides,
tudamis,
there'll be earthquakes.
If you're standing, you'll fall down.
All kinds of tremendous disruptions will
happen. Maybe even, you know, mass
extinctions of
living beings. Yeah. Okay.
Vsvs says, "Question by Sha, who is the
leftist extremist you suggest is worth
listening to or watching your books in
paperback?" My books will come out next
year, beginning next year. I'm working
on them right now, writing on writing
them.
Uh, who is the leftist extremist? I
suggest is worth listening or watching.
I I don't know any of them. I don't
listen to leftist extremists.
I'm sorry. It's not just what I do. So,
I can't really suggest somebody who's
worth listening or or watching. Leftist
extremist. Oh, I don't listen to any
leftist extremists. Sorry. Um hyphen
says can the brain rewire itself after
injury? Well depends on the type of
injury if there is see
and a brain injury means damage to the
neural tissue. So the brain has how is
the brain
con what is the architecture of the
brain? You have the scalp beneath the
scalp you have the skull which is pretty
thin actually. Beneath the skull you
have a she you know a layer of cerebral
spinal fluid. Below below that you have
the dura matter which is kind of a tough
outer covering of the brain. It's like
it's like a shower cap kind of thing.
The dura matter beneath the dura matter
you have the actual brain tissue. You
have various parts of the brain. The
brain has two hemispheres
and uh there is the outer brain. There's
the inner brain which is the more
reptilian brain. and so on and so forth.
And if the brain tissue is damaged
then you may you know experience various
forms of impairment based on what part
of the brain and to what extent it is
damaged. Now if there is an injury let's
say some part of the brain is damaged
can the brain rewire itself.
A lot of the times when the injury is
not very major, the brain somehow
adapts.
For example, there are people who
there have been medical procedures done
to people who extreme who experience
extreme or very severe epilepsy for
example in which the brain the
connection between the left and right
hemisphere of the brains is is cut. It's
severed
and they that kind of possibly has an
effect of ending the epileptic seizures
but the personality changes in some way.
There is that there are people who who
have lost half of their brain and they
still were able to function. There are
people who have fluid accumulation in
the brain and the brain is it's it's
only it only exists in one on one side
of the skull and they still function
properly. So if the injury is not very
traumatic,
the there's there's this case of this
American railroad worker for whom there
was a a metal bar that went through his
head. Obviously, it damaged his brain,
but he survived. It took out one of his
eyes, too. Uh let me find a you know,
American railroad
worker.
Brain brain
injury.
Brain injury.
Who was this guy for? Pineas gauge.
Phineas gauge.
Right there you have it. And this is the
rod that went through his
through his head. So he's a brain injury
survivor. It destroyed much of his
brain's left frontal lobe. So it depends
and he survived for several years. So it
depends on the extent of the injury,
what part of the brain is injured and
multiple factors. You can survive that,
you can continue possibly to have a
reasonably good life, but can the and
the brain seems to revive itself
somehow. It it changes the connections
in some way and it's able to adapt
and u give you as normal as as normal a
life as as as possible somehow.
Okay. Okay, Bishua says there are seven
stages of empire collapse and most
likely the US is in the sixth stage or
heading towards it. How much time will
it take to reach the seventh phase? I am
not aware of this theory of seven phases
or seven stages. So I can't say is the
US in the is in the is it in the sixth
stage really.
So there are various models of of an
imperial cycle. What's an imperial
cycle? the beginning of an empire, its
rise, then it's it's it's it plateaus at
the greatest extent at its zenith and
then there's a decline and eventually
the empire
abates or dissipates, crumbles, ceases
to exist. So that's an imperial cycle
and there are multiple theories in
political science
social mostly political science about
and and also in in history about
you know what are the what are the
phases of an imperial cycle I'm not
aware of these seven stages of imperial
collapse
most likely the US is in the sixth stage
I would disagree so if you have seven
stages and you are in the sixth stage it
means is you are in in terminal decline.
Is the US in terminal decline?
I would disagree. I think the US is
currently at the peak of its power.
There is obviously societal decay in the
US and that's what many people seem to
conrue as imperial decline. Societal
decay can obviously anytime be reversed.
There's also the fact that there are
competitors emerging to the US. One is
China, one is Russia. They are worried
about India also. now
but the US has never been as powerful as
it is right now.
So I disagree that the US is in terminal
decline. Sixth stage out of seven means
terminal decline and that is not how I
see it. So I disagree with that.
Now how much time will it take to reach
the seventh which is final collapse?
Can't say you never know what's going to
happen in the future. I am not a fortune
teller. I am not somebody who makes
predictions unlike some other people.
So I would say it may take 20 years, it
may take 200 years. I don't know. I
can't say. I am not in the business of
making predictions. Sometimes once in a
while I do. Once in a while I made a
prediction about Bangladesh, right?
Which came out to be true. But otherwise
I I I usually don't do that. So I will
not venture a suggest or a prediction
about when the US will collapse. I I
can't say.
God Spectre says Jesus's teachings are
misrepresented the most. What he speaks
makes perfect sense with the
understanding of Eastern philosophy said
sad. Um if you say so look I am not an
expert in um Christianity. I haven't
studied Jesus's teachings. Actually I
want to know want to hear a story.
Once when I was about probably 8 years
old, I was once stuck in a hotel for one
day.
Parents had some work and [snorts] so
on. So it was not like I was confined in
a jail cell. I was in a hotel room. Nice
hotel room with a TV and stuff to do.
Order food, do whatever you want. But I
didn't feel like watching TV. I was kind
of bored. So I opened a drawer in the
hotel. This is a hotel room in Europe
when I was a kid. I open a drawer and
there's this little Bible, little Bible,
pocket Bible. Um, they had kept there.
So I was like, okay, this is
interesting. Let's let's find out what
this religion is about. So at the age of
eight, in one day I finished the whole
book.
I read the entire book. It's kind of
interesting
to some extent. I I recall next to
nothing today. I I have said this so
many times. When you read something,
give yourself the permission to forget.
Don't try to memorize things. So, I just
read the whole thing as if it was a
story book. It was kind of interesting.
Made no impression on me. Otherwise, I
would have remembered something today.
I have read books at the age of my first
novel I ever read was at the age of
seven. I remember the entire story.
I remember the entire story. It was
called The Coral Island by Robert
Valentine. A very racist book actually.
But the first novel I read, it took me
seven days to read it and I remember the
entire story. It's a 19th century novel.
So I remember that. But I don't remember
anything about this Jesus book, the
Bible that I read when I was a kid, when
I was 8 years old in one in one day in a
hotel room in Europe in the city of
Geneva, Switzerland.
Right? So it it made no impression on
me. If it is such a great fantastic
thing, it would have made some
impression on me especially when I was 8
years old and so impressionable and so
eager to learn and learn things.
Uh anyway, see that's entirely my
perspective. Maybe I'm genetically
biased or whatever, right? Um to each
their own, I would say. Yeah, I am. See,
I have nothing against any specific
religion. I only have an issue with uh
with evil. See, colon foreign occupation
is evil. The attempt to colonize and
destroy nations is evil. Uh to give
religious justifications
to the destruction and genocide of
cultures and civilizations is evil. And
that sort of thing doesn't come out of
Hinduism or Buddhism or Janism,
right? It doesn't come out of Eastern
religions. So there's an issue with
certain kinds of religions. It looks
like Yeah, I may be completely wrong
about that. Yeah. But it looks like the
justification for
evil at scale seems to come out of
certain kinds of religions and that is
sad.
Vssvs says only Kanglu Mia from
superpower Bangladesh can beat America.
Bangladesh aura.
Okay sir. [laughter]
Okay. Uh, Nil Patil says, "Can India
form something like an African Union?
Why?
Don't do anything until unless it is of
great benefit to you.
Form something like the African Union
with whom? With whom? With African
nations? With other nations here? Have
you seen the kind of nations that
surround India?" The point is do
something if it makes sense from the
perspective of the Indian national
interest.
In episode 313, Za Ha questioned puppet
government rotation power.
Do you think USA also have rotating
power like the UK, Japan and Pakistan?
Okay, you are asking about
a revolving door policy in the in Japan
for example, prime ministers come and go
come and go. Only one prime minister has
made any kind of impact in Japan which
is Shinszu AB who has regrettably been
killed. The other prime ministers come
and go and after a few months don't you
don't even remember who was the previous
prime minister. So many prime ministers
come and go. In the UK the same thing in
Pakistan also the Americans have you
know
done similar things but in Pakistan
typically a leader
lasts a while typically. So the question
is does the US also have a rotating
power like like that? No. In in the US
the actual power center is hidden away
from from everyone's view. The
presidents come and go. American
presidents typically
rule
or or not rule but are in in in the hot
seat let's say typically for 4 to 8
years. See Trump is in his second um
term as president. Obama was there for 8
years. George W. Bush was there for 8
years. Bill Clinton was there for 8
years. Yeah. So, it's not a revolving
door situation. It's not as we can see.
But the the the real the crack of the
matter is that the American the
president of the US doesn't really have
the actual power. The actual power lies
somewhere behind the scenes. That's the
real thing.
All right. Putin 44 says, "Stuck in
corporate grind, mental and physical
health suffering. Worked hard but
labeled underperformer. How do you how
did you break free? Any advice?
How did I break free? See, if you want
to break free,
you need to have some kind of skills
that will pull you out of that domain
corporate work. So corporate grind means
you are working in in a in a corporation
in a company
and in a company you typically have
company processes and you have to rise
up the corporate lad l l l l l l l l l l
l l l l l l l l l l ladder by getting
promotions to get a promotion you need
to be shown as somebody you show that
you are a performer you to impress your
immediate manager and maybe the manager
above that person that sort of thing and
there's office politics and all that BS
right that's that's corporate life
um and yeah if If if that's something
you're not cut out for, it's going to
give you suffering, mental suffering. It
could if you are stuck sitting all day,
you may end up having physical health
suffering also. You may work hard but
yeah sometimes it doesn't you know you
don't because of various reasons you
don't get promotions. So what do you do?
How do you break free? One option is you
you resign and you go and work in a
different company. Maybe the atmosphere
is better there. Maybe the the the milu
is less toxic. That's one thing. But if
you want to escape corporate life
entirely, how do you do that? See,
you're asking how does a bird break free
from a cage?
So
if you're able to break free, you have
freedom. Now in human life, what is
freedom? The freedom to you asking how
do you gain the freedom to do what you
want with your life and your time?
And the straightforward simple answer is
you need money for that. So you either
have to save up some money that will
allow you to be free maybe for a year,
maybe two years, maybe the rest of your
life depending on how much money you're
able to save or
you need to have some other skills that
will break you out of corporate life and
maybe you start up something else. Maybe
you become an entrepreneur, maybe you
become a life coach, whatever, you know,
maybe you start a business of your own.
Or maybe you have just sufficient money
that you can retire for the rest of your
life. So the answer
to all these problems is money.
That's the hard answer.
How do you break free?
Money is the answer. You need money.
You either save up money or you earn
money. Two ways to acquire money.
Whatever income you're earning, you
either save as much as possible out of
it and eventually you have enough to to
break you free or you find some way of
earning money apart from what you're
doing and that maybe makes you free.
That's my advice.
I know it's not a shortcut. I know it's
not an easy solution. It's the hardest
solution. [laughter] But that life is
hard unfortunately. I'm sorry to say
that but it is. I cannot mislead you.
Your solution lies in money. You're
going to have to
make money, earn money, acquire money,
save money, whatever. That will break
you free. All the best, sir.
Mlevin says Robert,
Robert was a passenger in flight IC14.
Uh, Daru.
Yes, Daru. This is the Dar Daru is a
British currency printer and Roberto
Jiori was what the CEO the owner what
was he something like that right so Daru
a historic British company renowned
globally as a secure printer and paper
maker they were printing Indian currency
notes for some reason India had given
the contract to print Indian rupees
to this British company and the
Pakistanis were were also involved with
this company Okay. And this individual,
Roberto Jiori,
Roberto Jiori was a passenger on that
aircraft that was hijacked by Pakistani
terrorists in 19 what? 1999. Yeah.
[snorts]
So, Roberto,
what on earth? Gio.
Uh
this is uh some other jeiro
jior is it? Who is Guiiero Jiori?
Clearly not the guy who was in the
hijacked aircraft. Did he have uh
a son called Roberto?
So okay the the point is that the the
guy who was running the Laru or one of
the very important people of this
company was on that aircraft and that
kind of had um sort of a chain reaction
of of kinds of sorts.
Okay.
Hyphen says can you do the things can
you tell us the things India is doing
right?
India is doing a good job in
in growing its economy. The last quarter
it was 8% plus right 8% plus growth of
its GDP. India India is doing India has
done a tremendous job of breaking free
of the shackles of the previous
government and India is doing a great
job with its economy. Um
India's foreign policy is excellent. The
best foreign policy I I that India has
had since 1947.
Um India is doing great at
infrastructure building, building
highways, building airports,
building ports, all of that. India is
doing great. India clearly is doing
great when it comes to atmandera in
military technology. Obviously, it's
baby steps. It's it's step by step. We
take we put one foot in front of the
other. But there is this major focus now
on indigenizing technologies. We want to
manufacture jet engines over here. We
want to manufacture as many kinds of
weapons as possible within India itself
using indigenous technology. So there is
that is happening.
Uh so many things India is doing right.
What else?
Um yeah definitely foreign policy,
definitely infrastructure, definitely
the push for Atman
or definitely economic growth. I am
[snorts] I would say it can still do
better but definitely doing well in
economic growth. India is doing well.
India is doing great in dealing with
Pakistan.
India is doing great in in the in the
field of foreign policy. the way India
has uh um forged great relations with
nations in the West Asia region, in the
Gulf region,
in the Africa region. India has played a
major role in bringing the African Union
into the G20. So, India is doing a lot
of things right. Obviously, there are
things we are not doing that right also.
But the question is about what we're
doing right. So, I can think of these
these things off the top of my head. I'm
sure there's more. I'm sure there's
more.
Rahul says, "What could be the first
real applications of quantum computing?
How far along is India in this field and
how can this technology be weaponized?"
Well, quantum computing, what are the
real applications of quantum computing?
Uh secure communications,
uh breaking encryption,
uh when it comes to breaking encryption,
that is weaponization.
So quantum computing is
a technology that will allow computers
that use it to perform computations that
your standard computers cannot perform.
So there are certain operations that
would take a standard regular computer
like the ones we have we use all the
time, ones that are in our phones and so
on. um it would take several thousand
years for example and a quantum computer
can do it
in maybe half an hour maybe in a few
minutes and quantum computing uses
quantum mechanical properties and
phenomena such as quantum entanglement
uh superposition etc to perform uh
computations
especially super superposition
um
so if you want to let's say if you have
a very very complex password if you have
a secure system you have a very
complicated password in that is in terms
of hundreds of characters
including special characters and what
not and it's impossible to guess it then
what you can do is you can use a brute
force attack and a classical standard
computer will take centuries to do it
maybe thousands of years and a quantum
computer will break it in a can
potentially break it in in a matter of
minutes because it it does computations
entirely differently from a standard
computer. So that's one application and
that's weaponization of the technology.
Another application is the secure
communications that cannot be bro that
cannot be hacked because of the property
of entanglement.
So yeah these are some of the first
let's say real applications of quantum
computing. How far along is India in
this field? uh we it seems that we also
have a quantum computer somewhere in
India but I'm not sure how far we are
see India in India we have this tendency
to create technology demonstrators oh we
have developed the technology look at
this demonstrator look at this
demonstration happy done oh yeah bad job
that's the tendency India has in 1974 we
said they have tested a nuclear weapon
in Pran so let us now go to sleep for 25
years it was just a technology
demonstrator.
We do not actually intend to use this
technology. We just wanted to show the
world and impress the world that we are
very brilliant. So that's the deal with
India. Um
I hope that some real progress is being
done. So at least one quantum computing
system has been developed in India that
I'm aware of. I don't remember where it
was somewhere in the southern part of
India.
Um I'm not sure how much funding the
government is allocated to quantum
computing. Let's just quickly find out,
shall we?
uh how much funding
how much funding
has India allocated
to quantum computing let's see
national quantum mission 6,000 cr not
even $1 billion
India has allocated 6,000 cr rupees $750
million for its national quantum when
you are allocating less than a billion
dollar to quantum computing. What? What?
What are we doing?
Look, for you and me, a million dollars
is a lot of money. I know that.
[laughter]
But from a national perspective, when
you're allocating less than a billion
dollars
to something as important as your
national contamation, what are we doing?
Looks like we have no ambition. Looks
like we are doing everything, you know.
uh in a non-s serious way. So there we
have it. I suppose what you can do is
give each engineer and scientist a
salary of 15,000 rupees and then
maximize the use of the money. That's
what India excels at. What are the
scientists? What are the salaries of the
engineers in ISRO? What is the average
salary? Let's find out. Okay.
Um
average salary
in salary
in isro
let's find out the average salary
significantly
15 20 lakhs annually so if it is 15
lakhs annually it's about one lakh a
month one and a I don't know one and a
half lakhs a month no less than that if
it's 20 it's one and a half And once you
take out the tax and all how much do you
get?
Starting salaries 4 to9 lakhs. I mean we
pay our
engineers and scientists so less.
How will we motivate people? And then we
have what less than a billion dollars
are located. So I'm not sure what we're
doing really honestly.
Uh K23 or 40 says are landlocked nations
always at a disadvantage. For example,
Ethiopia wants to go to war for
Eritrea's port access.
It's not always a disadvantage.
In the
12th century AD, there was this little
landlocked nation called Mongolia. Do
you know [laughter] do you know what it
did?
So, it's not always going to be a
disadvantage. What really makes or
breaks a nation or determines the future
of a nation and the
fate of a nation is the quality of its
leadership.
That's what truly matters. If you have a
worldclass once in a century kind of
leader, you may be landlocked, you may
be a little island, you may still rule
the world. Look at England.
Little island, they ruled the entire
world once. their descendants still rule
the world.
Right? So there was a sealocked nation.
Mongolia was a landlocked nation. There
is no such thing.
Whatever constraints you face are mostly
psychological constraints. There's
always a way out. There's always a way
to achieve whatever you want as long as
you have the the wherewithal to do it.
Okay. Slendies says, "How do you stay
focused for 6 hours without stopping
working? How to deal with the
distraction when hustling? How to not
get up until it's done? I am How do I
stay focused
for let's say six hours without stopping
my work? Well, I do work that I find
interesting.
I do work that I find interesting, that
I find exciting.
Nobody has told me what to do, right? I
decide what I do. I don't have a boss. I
don't take orders from a boss. My boss
is me. I with the blessings in of the
gods am in a situation in a position in
life where I decide what I do.
So I give myself the order to do the
most interesting work I can do. I have a
number of projects that I work I'm
working on and these are projects I have
chosen because I find them super
interesting and super exciting. So when
you're doing that sort of work, why will
you not be able to focus on it? And
let's say that you are doing a task.
It's super exciting, super fascinating,
super interesting. You chose the task,
you're doing it. But it's possible after
working on it for 2 three hours, your
brain may say enough. I need a break. In
that case, what I do is I switch to a
different different task. So now the
brain can switch off from that and do
something differently. So you can
continue the work, right? So that's what
I do. Now, how do you deal with
distractions when hustling?
Well, the it's impossible to completely
avoid distractions, right? What you can
do is change your environment
as much as possible.
If you have 78 distractions in the room
that you're working in, there's going to
be a problem. If you take all the
distractions and put them outside as far
away as possible, then you will be less
prone to distractions. If you are doing
some serious work, but you have your
phone next to you and blah blah blah
going on and whatever, social media and
whatnot, messages, notifications,
then you're going to be tempted to look
at what's happening. What's happening?
What's happening? So,
control your environment
in such a way that as many distractions
as possible are removed. That's what you
do. And how to not get up until it's
done.
Well, decide how long no how to not get
up until it's done.
Well, that comes from discipline.
Discipline means discipline is a muscle
that you train. Let's say you are thin
and you want to get big. So, you go to
gym, you lift weights, let's say 5 days
a week and you do it for 12 months at a
stretch, right? In a proper way. That's
how you bulk up. And obviously, you have
to eat the right diet. And the more you
do it, the more disciplined you get. So
discipline is about being consistent,
doing it over and over again. And the
more consistent you are, the more the
easier it becomes for you to be
disciplined. So that's how you do it.
All right. All the best.
Rahul says, "Will reducing population
growth lead to a better quality of life
considering it might cause fertility
issues later on? How do we manage?" Um,
reducing population growth [snorts]
is going to make the population age
faster. It will raise the median age of
the population as time goes by.
That means that you will have fewer and
fewer young people in your population
which is not good for the population
which is not good for the future of the
nation.
So if you want better quality of life
you have to reduce not population growth
but
population itself. So let's say India
sets up
50 bases on Mars and each base can let's
say accommodate a million people. So and
and then we ask for volunteers who among
Indian citizens wants to go and live on
Mars for the rest of their life. We'll
give you a great lifescent there. So
then
so then we are able to send 50 million
people to Mars. then maybe the
population becomes less without doing
anything nasty and then you will have
better quality of life because there'll
be less competition for resources.
So that's how you do it. By reducing
population growth, you're going to cause
tremendous problems down the line.
So how do you manage? Obviously we don't
have 50 Mars bases. We don't have a
single Mars base or a moon base. What do
we do? How do we manage? We bring the
population down over a couple of
centuries.
We have to control the TFR. We have to
fine-tune the TFR.
You know, right now it's two or or 1.9
which is bad. The replacement level TFR
is 2.1. Maybe we can make it 2.05
for the next 50 years
for the next 200 years maybe. Then it
comes down very slowly very gradually.
That sort of thing is what we need to
do. Uh VSBS says do you think IT coolies
are good people? Why not?
See it is a derogatory word
actually it's it's it's I mean it's not
a nice thing to say about people who are
working in IT.
Why why will there not be nice people?
Cyber coolies right? I mean I am guilty
of using the term.
I have been one myself.
I I think I'm a reasonably good person.
I was one too, right? Look, everyone
most people are nice people. Most people
are good people.
If you look at any nation, any
population, most people are just decent,
hardworking people. There's only a small
segment of any population that's going
to have non good qualities.
And that's something you'll see
everywhere. So why are IT workers not
good people? Of course they are good
people. Most of them are.
Gpati says I am from Tamil Nadu and the
situation here is bad. Hindu temples
controlled by a guy called Shaker Babu
who is a crypto Christian. Tamil ladu
needs another Ragunata kilawan. Google
him up. Cross more danger than Christ.
Okay sir. Uh my policy is I don't
discuss internal politics in these
matters. So I thank you for what um uh
for the information you have given. Uh
but I don't discuss u
India's internal politics. I don't
discuss inter religious conflicts within
India.
So yeah that's what I can say. See the
thing is I can't fight every fight in
the world. Obviously there are problems
in India. I have spoken about this.
There are problems in India. One of the
problems in India is the industrial
scale convergence
to foreign religions that are happening
within India. Definitely big issues and
in some states you have way more of that
than than in other states. Uh but
so that's what I can say and thank you
for the information you have given
and I hope that the great land of Tamil
Nadu will do well again.
Right. right now maybe it's not doing
that well like you're reporting to us
the Tamil people are fantastic some of
the nicest people you'll meet in the
world
such rich history such rich
history of Hinduism
in Tamil Nadu such devoted people you
will find most of the time so I hope
that things get better I hope
Uh VSVS says what was your opinion on
being celibate before marrying? Do you
think the modern norm contrary to this
is dharmic?
I think ideally you should
be celibate before marrying.
We are
human beings.
We are different from animals. Right? We
have something called an instit
institution of marriage. The institution
of marriage is the basis of civilized
existence.
That is what differentiates us from
animals.
So ideally you should remain celibate
before marrying. It's not like you know
what before I stick before I decide on
on on one cake I want to try every shade
every flavor of other cakes and ice
cream and all that. What what is this?
Are we dogs? Are we animals? Even dogs
don't do that.
Uh I think it is adharmic to indulge in
such behavior. Many of you may disagree.
That's fine.
Um that's what I believe.
You in life you should be loyal to one
person in my opinion.
Prattana says Indo Greek coins show them
in bandana crowns which suspicially
suspiciously looks like our priest
king's bandana. The resemblance is
fascinating. Let's take a look. Okay.
Uh, Indo Greek coins
coins. Coins.
Okay. Let's see.
Okay. You have millinda. This this No,
this is art
armidoros.
He is wearing what seems to be a
bandanna kind of thing. This gentleman
here also is wearing a bandana.
This is Smaya. No, Apollo Dusi.
He also is wearing a bandana. Yeah. This
this is obviously Kaneshka. This is a
person Milander Milinda who's wearing a
helmet.
Who is this? Hermayos who is also
wearing a bandana kind of thing on his
head. Very interesting. And obviously
when we talk about the so-called priest
king, you don't know if it was a priest
king or who he was, but
yeah, this this very celebrated famous u
statueette
this person this gentleman is also
wearing a bandana kind of thing that
same sort of thing on his head. Very
interesting. A very interesting pattern
you have pointed out over here. The
resemblance is indeed fascinating.
Yeah. But we don't have this today and
that that tradition seems to have been
discontinued at some point in time. But
yeah, that's an interesting pattern that
you have discovered here. I will dig
deeper into this. Thank you. Chinti
Anand says, "Same reason for Austrian
painters book or which same reason? You
clearly are referring to something I
discussed some time ago, but uh I have
taken so many questions I don't remember
what it was about, but okay.
Chinu says, "Do you believe in parto
principle? Is it applicable everywhere?
When are you going to make a video on
raising standards?" Okay. Do I believe
on in the parto principle? I think it it
is it's a principle that makes sense.
Of all the work you do, it's only a
small fraction of it that actually
brings in most of your results
indeed.
Then if you take the parallel principle
to the next level that 20% of the work
you do gives 80% of your results then if
you take 20% of the 20% that's only four
what
4%
whatever the number is so that gives you
about half of your results so yeah it
actually does make sense I have seen
this in my own experience roughly 20% or
something of your work gives you most of
your results indeed. Is it applicable
everywhere? I'm sure it's not applicable
everywhere. It's applicable in in
productivity
mainly in productivity in the kind of
work you do and all. It's not applicable
everywhere. It's not of law of nature.
It's not a physical law, law of
the natural universe, but it kind of
applies in productivity. When am I going
to make a video on raising standards?
See, I did this whole
series of 50 live streams in which I'm
sitting on camera and working non-stop
for 8 hours. That is raising standards.
That is a series. That was a series on
raising standards because that kind of
serves to show you how much work it
takes to make anything to do anything
meaningful.
You have to be genuinely dedicated
and you really really have to work hard.
So that was a series on raising
standards. I could make a series of
videos in which I talk about
specific aspects of raising standards. I
could do that too. Maybe it will
something maybe it'll be something I do
this coming year but I haven't decided
yet. All right. Uh Pratarana says China
hypes but India hides capabilities. Why?
I think it's the other way around. India
loves to boast. China hides its
capabilities but once you become so big
that the capabilities can't be hidden
that's when you talk about them. For the
longest time, China hid everything.
Denging Shaoping had this this maxim,
right? Hide your time. Hide hide your
strength and b your time. Means you keep
quiet, don't boast, work as hard as
possible, grow your economy, grow your
industrial base and when the time is
right, you can talk about it. So that's
what China did. China, China kept very
quiet until about 2012.
But India,
we love to boost, boost, boost, boost,
which is a big problem. I see it the
other way around. India doesn't hide its
capabilities. India tries to boast.
Indians love to boast. The Chinese keep
quiet. That's that's the problem.
Okay. Bonish Sab Sabrina Sabrina says,
"I met you at I met you this year at the
Jost Summit. It was a dream come true
moment for me as a follower for three
years." Thank you so much, sir. Um
[snorts]
I don't re I'm sure if I see see your
face I'll be able to remember you. Uh
but um yeah I met lots of people there
and I was I I can't remember the face
right now. So I'm just thinking which
one but anyway thank you so much for
being a follower for follow for 3 years.
I'm sure it was a great pleasure to meet
you in Jaipur and I look forward to
meeting you in the future as well. All
right sir. Do well. Thank you so much.
Thank you so much for being a follower
for three years. Thank you so much.
UMX G Laha says, "Does one require
excessive mathematics or knowledge of
science to be good at developing
software or computer related stuff?" No,
you need to if you want to develop
software, you need to have a logical
mind. You need to understand how logic
works. There are people who can't
understand mathematics until it is
represented in in term in in terms of in
terms of uh in computer code in
programming language maybe Python code
maybe C code whatever let's say you are
doing integration triple integration
okay now integration is something you
learn in calculus
let's say you're doing triple
integration along three variables
or let's say you're doing a 4year
transform
What on earth is a 4y year transform? No
one understands this until but but it's
to many people it makes sense when you
write the code for a 4 year transform.
So you don't need knowledge of
mathematics or science to be good at
developing software. You need to have a
logical mind and you need to you need to
learn the programming languages properly
or one language right depending on what
kind of work you're doing. So yeah, you
don't need
any knowledge of mathematics. You your
mind needs to be sound and logical.
That's all.
Bijua says, "Did you watch Oppenheimer
film? I think it's boring. I kind of
find it boring. I watched it." Yeah.
See, there are some movies when you
watch them, you remember the story. You
remember the the visuals for a long long
long time.
Oppenheimer, I don't remember the
visuals. It was kind of dull and boring.
I do remember kind of the story, some
bits and pieces of it. I I
don't remember all the characters. It
was not that great. It was okay for a
one time watch for for a one time
viewing. It's not something that's
memorable for me. Yeah. So, I I agree
with you. Abishek says, "Did the US
engineer COVID 19 to derail Chinese
economy? It's stuck at 18 trillion."
Well, how will I know? How will I know?
I don't know can't say
it's possible but we don't have any
evidence so I cannot really say okay
Monish Sabrina says I am a PhD student
planned to work on artificial biological
cells but because of my supervisor
supervisor I changed to regular cancer
research my curiosity and research is
crushed what should I do it's becoming
heavy day by day
what I would recommend
see this This is a common problem that
PhD students face in India. I should
know. I've been there.
What I will recommend to you is this.
Swallow the pain.
Whatever it takes, get your degree
and then
go somewhere where you can actually do
the work you want to do.
Indian supervisors most of them are
third rate people some of them are great
no question but most of them are just
average mediocre people who have no
interest in whatever research they are
they are doing often time they will
steal half of their students research if
a student does some work they will the
work will be published but the
supervisor's name will be first as the
primary author there's all kinds of
problems what I will tell you is just
get your PhD degree do the research
Get it done. Write up your thesis. Get
the viva done. Get the degree.
Do some publications in the meanwhile.
Get a few publications in your name.
Even if you are not the primary author,
as long as you are one of the authors,
it's fine. And then
go and do the research wherever it is
being done. Maybe in this country, maybe
outside the country, whatever, whatever
it is. All right? That's what I would
recommend to you. Don't give up. Get the
degree and then find a way to do the
research you want to do. All right.
Mish, all the best. Do well.
Saga Dadimani says, "I'm 24. I had eight
intestine surgeries. O get infection
frequently. I'm not able to focus on
studies also brain injury. Failing to
quit MBA government seat guide me."
I'm so sorry to hear about this this
issue, the health issue. Eight intestine
surgeries. My goodness, [clears throat]
I'm so sorry that you had to go through
this, my friend. Um, you get infections
frequently, not able to focus on
studies, also brain injury, feeling to
quit MBA seat, MBA government seat. Um,
how can I guide you about this?
First of all, you need to get your
health sorted.
There's there's obviously some issue.
You need to get the right medical
treatment done. Maybe you need to change
doctors. If if your doctors or your
hospital is not able to solve the
problem and you're having this repeated
infections or whatever it is,
maybe you should go to somebody else,
get a second, third, fourth opinion and
find somebody who will cure you. That's
the first thing you have to do
because without health you have nothing.
If you are let's say you are a korati,
you're a billionaire. Let's say you have
will have you will have a 100 problems
in life. But if you are a billionaire
with health issues, you only have one
problem. The other problems go away. My
point is please sort out your health
first of all.
Focus on that.
Um if you have to postpone your MBA for
a while or whatever, do that. But look,
if your if your health is going to
continue like this, ah that's going to
be a problem for you. So your first
focus, your main focus should be on your
health.
If it's infection or something, it
should be treatable and there should be
a permanent cure for that.
And if if you if you have surgery after
surgery, you obviously I can understand
you can't focus on studies. It will
affect other parts of the the body also
eventually.
Uh so my my main advice to you is first
of all, please take care of your health.
Get this sorted. Get this fixed. maybe
change doctors, change hospital,
whatever. Find a proper permanent
solution to this. Then
then take a focus on the studies.
That's what I would say. So once again,
I'm I'm really sorry to hear that you
had to go through this. You're still
perhaps going through it. Please sort
out your health, get healthy, then do
everything else. All the best, my
friend. Sager
Hersai. Uh it says it says I was
flirting with a random Pakistani girl
and guess what? They know more about us.
Some complex questions were asked by her
on Hinduism but I managed. What are my
thoughts? Um
what are my thoughts? [laughter]
How did you find a random you mean
flirting online
or did you meet the person in real life?
Um what are my thoughts?
Okay. So she
they know more about us.
Okay. And she asked some complex
questions about Hinduism and you were
able to manage. So it's a good thing
that they are they are curious about
their own heritage. See Pakistanis their
what is their heritage?
Their heritage is our heritage.
Their ancestors
practice Hinduism. So it is but natural
for at least some of them those those
who have reasonable amount of
intelligence to be curious about
their own ancestral heritage and the
culture and civilization of their
ancestors. So
it's a good thing. It's a good thing.
That's my thought. [laughter]
Yeah.
Um
Bossman says can you tell how passport
indexes are calculated? Um most passport
rankings are based on how many nations
give you visa-free access.
[snorts] So if you are a nation
let's say you are nation X
which means that you are a passport
holder of nation X and if 40 other
nations give your nation visa free
access which means you can simply take
the passport and without taking a visa
you can go to the country and enter then
your score is 40. But if you are a
nation why and a 100 nations offer you
visa-free access then your score is 100
which is greater than 40 and if you are
Japan with 190 countries that give you
visa free access then you are number one
on the rankings so it is based on how
many nations give you visa free access
visa free entry to your citizens that's
how passport indexes are calculated
that's that's what I know if there are
some other rankings based on some other
factors I don't know but that's what I
have seen
Okay. King Ritwick says, "I am a class
10 student from Saint Xavier
Bhuberneshwar." Bhubneshwar. Okay.
Debate competition topic was India's
freedom struggle. Uh I saw your video on
Mr. Gandhi continued. Uh there's a
continuation somewhere. Okay. Uh King
Rituk says, "I completely memorized and
made notes in based on my video on how
Mr. Gandhi was a British agent and
compared between Mr. Gandhi and Lincoln.
I delivered it. [laughter]
Okay. Let's see what happened then. Uh
when I was speaking, everyone was
shocked. My friends clapped for me. I
became a role model for my juniors.
Friends, juniors were amazed. Except for
the teachers naturally. Naturally, your
teachers will not like it. Okay.
[laughter]
Then what happened?
But then I got scoldings from all my
teachers and who said you cannot say all
these things. Principal sir said you
have to bring your parents on Monday.
What will happen
my dear friend Rywick?
Well,
you are brave.
You are also slightly immature. But I
I'm proud of you. [laughter]
Everyone is immature at your age. But
you had the courage to do something
which others will not dare to do.
So you have the quality of courage.
But if you my recommendation to you is
to use your courage wisely.
See when you say what I what you did
about Mr. Gandhi in front of your
teachers you are guaranteed to get a
scolding. They will now see you as a as
a as a bad person. Mr. Gandhi is the
father of our nation. He is the Mahatma.
How can you say such things? There has
to be something wrong with you. Now the
principal will obviously ask your
parents to come on Monday. What's going
to happen? Well, what's going to happen
depends on your parents. Now, do your
parents also regard Mr. Gandhi as a
Mahatma.
Do they regard him as a saint? In that
case, you will get school from your
parents too. But listen, that's okay.
That's okay. You don't have to agree
with everything your parents believe in.
Maybe your parents uh don't have this
right information. It's also possible,
right? So clearly
you understand
what tr what Mr. Gandhi truly was about
and sometimes you have to stand up for
for what you believe in and if that
means that you're going to get a
scolding
well so be it. So
I would again say I'm proud of you. I
would if I were in a position
what I would do okay I'm just giving an
alternative
an alternative to to to what can be done
if I were in your position with the
wisdom that I have today at this age but
if I was in your position what I would
do is I would say all these things to my
friends but I would not say it on the
stage in front of my teachers because I
know the teachers won't understand and
they will now label me as a
troublemaker. So now that all this has
happened, call your parents to the
principal's office. I as a kid I've also
been there. [laughter]
Okay. But before you take your parents
there, you tell them exactly what
happened so that there is no surprise
for your parents and then let the your
parents decide. If they stand with you,
good. If they don't stand with you, if
they schooled you, if they're unhappy,
then that will pass. Okay? But anyway, I
really I really commend your courage. I
applaud your courage. But I would say
be a little more judicious in the
future. You don't have to you should
ideally not say these things in front in
front of your teachers. Teachers can
create a lot of trouble in the in
context of the Indian education system.
And if they label you as a troublemaker,
they they could make your life a little
more little more difficult. Anyway,
Ritwick, uh once again, I'm proud of
you. Uh if if you get scoldings and all
that, don't be discouraged. You clearly
are a brave, courageous, and intelligent
person. And use these qualities wisely
and you will do great in life. Right?
the the things that we go through when
we are young, when we are children, when
we are teenagers, they shape our
character and those memories eventually
they may sometimes be traumatic when you
go through them, but in the when you
grow up, you may kind of remember them
as something that was not that that bad
big of a deal. Anyway,
all the best with all the best.
Okay, what's the next question? Uh
Aradush Dwashilli says apart from first
principles a shed light on how to think.
How to think?
How to think? Um thinking comes
naturally to us.
Uh
thinking, how to think?
[snorts]
Thinking is something that comes
naturally. But is there structured
thinking? Structured thinking is
obviously you use mental models for
thinking. Now I am pretty sure I use
multiple mental models to think but I
don't know what these mental models are
called because I have never opened a
book of mental models and decided I will
use this pattern of thinking or that
model of thinking. I probably have
developed me mental models on my own
knowingly or unknowingly since well
since the beginning. Um
so I'm not sure how to explain that.
That's that's actually a very good
question. How to think? How to think? So
I'll have to think about how to how to
communicate this to you all.
So right now I don't have an answer to
this question. I'll have to first think
about it.
How to communicate how to think? Of
course I know how to think but how do I
communicate that?
And I have not thought about how what
are the patterns and structures to my
thinking process. Obviously
I use multiple structured processes that
are probably called mental models. So
what I love to do is I love to think
about it. And how do I think about
things properly? Let me let me explain
this to you. How to think?
We all think all the time. Some people
believe it's overthinking. Some people
believe whatever. For me, my brain is
on. I'm always thinking something.
Okay. But if you want to think properly
in a structured fashion, how do you how
do you do that? You do it by writing
your thoughts down on paper, not on a
keyboard, on paper, pen on paper.
And when you do that, it crystallizes
your thoughts. It focuses you. It it
forces you to think in a structured
manner. And when you write things down,
you can immediately see if there are
defects, deficiencies, or flaws in your
thinking. and then you can amend that
and restructure that. So one of the ways
to think clearly or to improve your
thinking
is by writing. So that's that's one
insight I can give you but I love to
think about this in detail by writing
about it. Okay. Okay. How many it's 3
hours 21 minutes. I still have 37 super
chats to take. Please stop taking super
chats otherwise I'll be stuck here
forever. [laughter]
Which is a privilege. It's a privilege
that you all ask me these questions but
uh let us end it soon for this session.
Obviously we'll keep doing it. I'll keep
taking super chats. So yeah 3 and a half
hours is a little long. Okay. Time space
theory says sun god has seven horses
that are vibure.
Brahma breath represents the cycles time
cycles. If these are abstract ideas why
do you call them mythology and not
science? because ancient math was also
in the form of verses. Okay?
See, if I lived in the
in the second millennium BC,
20,000 BC, let's say, or or 1800 BC,
then I would call of the call all of
these things science
because at that time, let's say 1800 BC,
we did not have the knowledge and the
data that we have today. We did not know
at the time
what was the spectrum of hydrogen. What
were the spectra that you could observe
from galaxies? We did not know that
galaxies were receding at a certain rate
from us. We did not know there was
something called cosmic microwave
background radiation.
We did not know
that
atoms have energy levels. The atomic
theory was kind of known right. um he
put forth the atomic theory but we do
not know that atoms are made of what
subatomic particles protons neutrons
electrons we do not know that electrons
can only occupy certain shells
energy levels
because of the that's the bas of quantum
mechan all these things that we know
today we did not know at the time
so if I was a person who lived around
1800 BC I would consider all these
things to be science science
that science evolves.
So what we call science today maybe in
2,000 years will will sound like
superstition or mythology.
Right?
My point is from today's perspective
what was considered to be science 3,000
4,000 years ago is no longer science. In
2,000 years from today, what we consider
to be science today will be considered
very basic. That is my point. From
today's perspective, from my
perspective, if you're talking physics,
you're talking about observable
evidence, about empirical physical
objects and phenomena.
We're talking about everything with a
mathematical foundation which means
everything has [clears throat]
you can describe it mathematically
through equations. Okay, I hope I have
explained what I mean by science today
and what is no longer science from
today's perspective.
I'm not trying to deride you or offend
you. I understand your perspective.
But once you study science rigorously
properly then you will understand the
difference between what is today science
and what is today no longer scientific
in nature. So when we talk about seven
horses which are vibure
how do I
put that in a scientific perspective?
What is brahma breath? It is an
allegory, let's say, for cycles of time,
abstract ideas or whatever you want to
call it. But how do I create a physical
theory out of that that is underpinned
by mathematics?
Doesn't work like that, right? I I'm
sure you may agree or disagree, which is
perfectly good. You have the right to
disagree.
But I would recommend that if you are
genuinely interested in these matters in
these topics then get yourself a proper
modern scientific education and then
decide for yourself whether you still
agree with this or not. And look if
you're a scientist for example you don't
necessarily have to be an atheist.
I'm not saying that you have to you have
to be atheistic and all that. There are
plenty of scientists who are absolutely
not a atheists.
So yeah that's that's my perspective. I
hope I have given some kind of clarity
about how I see things and obviously
many of you probably may disagree with
that which is perfectly fine. Please
feel free to disagree. Uh we don't have
to agree on everything
but the disagreement should be healthy
and constructive. So maybe you can try
and try and understand what I'm trying
to say here. what the perspective is.
Science is a discipline and if you are a
scientist, you have to be disciplined
and structured in your thinking. You
cannot take liberties that go beyond the
real the boundaries of what is
considered to be proper science today.
Kiran Mur says Google and Microsoft
investing in India to make data centers
in the future. Is this a good thing for
India in the upcoming future?
Data center is like a well or a pot that
we will put some pots in India in which
we will dump data.
So to create a data center you
buy storage instead of the storage
facilities in India. What does India
gain from that? money perhaps
u it will consume a tremendous amount of
power which is fine but does India gain
some new knowledge some new technology
from this not really
I'm not sure what how this helps India
tremendously
what India needs is indigenous
technological capabilities
Google sets up a big data center in
India maybe how much employment will it
generate data centers very little
employment
I don't know what is the benefit of this
for India actually. Yeah. Ryik P says
why is India not aggressive at least in
the subcontinent.
You may have heard me say this that when
it comes to Western Europe, Western
Europe which is the major power there.
It's the United States. It's not France.
It's not Germany. It's none of the
European nations. It's the United States
which is the most powerful nation in
Western Europe. Even though it's not
physically in Western Europe. Now when
it comes to the Indian subcontinent,
which is the most powerful nation? It is
the United States.
I hope that answers the question.
Marshall says, "Have you watched Durand
yet? If not, are you planning to watch
it? Love your insights." Look,
[laughter]
I did watch it. I answered this question
like three times today. Uh
so I'll not explain again again all over
again in detail. It's a great movie. I
watched it. I really enjoyed it. I look
forward to seeing the sequel. I really
liked the movie. Like the movie a lot
which is a big surprise to me because
and I broke my own rule of not watching
Hindi movies, not not watching Bollywood
movies and I'm glad I did. Great movie
overall.
Monish says, I have seen people saying
we don't eat beef but we eat other
cattle meat in the past. I personally
don't eat any cattle meat but this
confuses me.
Um,
see when we talk about the word cattle,
what do we mean? We talk about the
animals that belong to the boine family.
Boine. So, what animals does this
include? It includes cows. It includes
buffaloos. Buffaloos are not cows,
right? They're different. They look like
cows that similar face like cows, but
they have a bigger body and different
slightly different bone structure. They
were black skin, different shape of
horns. So, they are like cousins of the
cow. Then you have yaks. Yaks are like
gigantic hairy thick thick furry cows
that exist that live in the Himalayas,
right? Uh they are perfectly at home in
sub-zero temperatures, snow and all.
They they are happy there. U regular cow
can't be there. So boine animals are
cows, yaks, buffaloos,
gore. You know gore, the Indian, the
world's largest boine beast. Gore. G A U
R Gore. this gigantic beast, the world's
largest boine animal, incredibly
[snorts] powerful, super muscular. So
that's also
a boine animal, you could consider it to
be wild cattle.
So um
so in in what we call Hinduism or Hindu
Dharma, obviously we don't eat beef.
That's the biggest taboo. But you can
eat buffalo. Yeah.
From my perspective,
cow and buffalo are almost the same
[laughter]
actually. But yeah, in Hinduism, you can
eat buffalo meat. So,
you know, you it's up to you. If you
don't eat cattle meat, then don't eat
cattle meat. If some see Hinduism is
super super plural. So many different
traditions are part of Hinduism. So many
different ways of life are part of
Hinduism. And some of these may not make
sense to a lot of people, but they are
still part of our culture. So even if it
some some of these things may make some
of us uncomfortable,
we have to respect that this is also
part of our culture for some of us.
It is what it is. Okay. Uh Ankita Kacham
has gifted 20 memberships of the
channel. Thank you so much ma'am. You
are so kind. Thank you so much. I I I
really appreciate that. Thank you.
Shaa Sha Shonak Kokate says Rani Tarabai
despite being a woman in the 1700s in
the 1700s led Maratas to victory after
all male hairs and all hope was lost
ending the 27-year Marata war of
independence yet remains unsung and
unheard. So I have not studied Marata
history in any significant detail
because of posity of time and whatn not.
But let us see about Rani Tarabay. So
I'm not aware of this this great lady.
Rani Tarabai Bosel 1675 to 1761 was a
legendary Marata warrior queen
daughter-in-law of Chhatrapati Shivaji
Maharaj and regent of the Marata Empire
who fiercely led resistance against the
Muggal Empire after her Raj husband Raja
Ram's death.
Okay.
Okay. Okay. Ensuring the Marata kingdom
survival and expansion through her
military genius, administrative skills,
and unwavering courage against Orang's
forces. Okay. I'll not go into further
detail, but wow. Okay.
You see
and and well, and we don't know so much
about her. Very few people apparently
know about her. She remains unsung and
unheard. Well, well, thank you for
pointing this out, Shak.
I I will uh look up the life and career
of this great lady
and uh I will recommend that whoever is
interested in marata history or history
Indian history should do the same too.
All right sir thank you so much for
pointing this out.
Sab Mahajan says how do tectonic plates
decide where to move next? It's like
asking how does the wind or the clouds
decide to where to move next? The winds
don't have a consciousness. The clouds
aren't conscious. They don't decide what
to do. It is the forces of nature
that govern what happens to the winds to
the clouds. Similarly to tectonic
plates.
So how is the earth structured
internally? At the very center of the
earth you have a solid metallic core
iron and nickel mostly. It is under so
much pressure from the entire weight of
the of the earth that it it is metallic.
It's extremely hot.
Above that you have metallic liquid
metallic nitrogen um not what nickel and
and iron. It's it's liquid and it's it's
flowing. It's not stationary. It's
flowing
and it's under extreme pressures and
temperatures. It is ionized which gives
rise to the earth's magnetic field.
Above that you have the magma layer.
Magma. Magma is molten rock.
So that also flows around, slloshes
around.
Above that you have the earth's mantle.
Above that you have the earth's crust.
So above the molten magma layer you have
non molten rock and that is in the form
of these massive tectonic plates. If you
have seen tea with milk at a high
temperature, you pour it into a cup and
you let it sit for a while, it will
develop a layer of of [snorts]
cream, right? Of of of thin solid layer.
The Earth's crust is like that. Below it
is all molten rock.
And the movement of the molten rock, the
liquid, it moves the tectonic plates
around. And that's how tectonic plates
which are floating on top of the liquid
liquid magma that's why they keep moving
around over very long geological time
scales. So they don't decide what to do.
It is the forces of physics the laws of
physics and the forces of nature that
decide how they move.
Okay. Arbut says what if India [snorts]
ramps up if its defense budget to 5% GDP
suddenly? Well, we will suddenly have a
lot of money to to invest in our
military upkeep, in our military
expenditure. So, we will be able to,
let's say, procure way more missiles,
maybe maybe set up way more production
lines for fighter aircraft. Maybe build
way more submarines that we currently
are trying to build. Maybe if we have 50
warships that are being constructed
right now, maybe we'll be able to have
50 more being constructed,
maybe 100 more being constructed. Yeah.
Right. So, yeah, it will be great for
the military. It will be great for our
our national defense, national offense
also. Yeah, that's what will happen.
Rojett says the other day I was quoting
the definition of consciousness directly
from Ka Upanishad. The most profound
definition I have found ac far so far
across all philosophies and
neuroscience. Let us see what's the
definition of consciousness. Uh hoad
uh conscious
consciousness what's it say?
The ka opishad explores consciousness by
questioning the ultimate source behind
our senses and mind revealing that
Brahman the ultim the brahman ultimate
reality isn't an object of perception
but the very seer in the eye the hearer
in the ear the thinker in the mind and
beyond them it teaches the true
realization comes from um
okay this is a philosophical definition
or phil philosophical talk about
consciousness I am talking about a
scientific definition of consciousness
and once again one has to understand
that philosophy and science are
different science does come from
philosophy But science has very strict
boundaries. Science has very strict
discipline. We don't talk about
um non-physical objects and phenomena.
Um [clears throat] so I am [laughter]
looking for a physical definition of
consciousness. A definition of
consciousness that is constrained by the
laws of physics
which will also apply to neuroscience.
by the way because neuroscience is also
constrained by the laws of physics.
So I haven't found one yet. Nobody has
found one. We have definitions from
philosophy.
We have various philosophical views on
consciousness which actually should
inspire scientists but these are not
scientific definitions.
But anyway thank you for for pointing
this out sir Rajat G. Thank you. Animeh
Paul says, "Long time viewer here."
Thank you. Love your work. Thank you so
much. Thank you so much. Really
appreciate all my viewers. Well, this
channel wouldn't I wouldn't be doing all
this if I did not have you all as my
viewers. It's a privilege to have you
all and I never do take it for granted.
So, thank you so much Animesh. Thank
you.
Shivanch says, "Araali range gave us
gave us one of the greatest kingdoms in
the past 1500 years, Madar. And now the
government wants to destroy them
geologically. Does it make sense? I have
not looked into this. I am not aware of
what's going on. There seems to be some
controversy. Obviously, if there's a
controversy, there must be some real
issue, but I have not looked into it.
And even if I do look into it, this is a
internal political matter most likely.
So, I will most likely still not comment
about it. I
I have my own rules and policies. I
don't discuss Indian internal politics.
So anyway, but I'm not aware of what's
going on. I still haven't looked into
it, so can't say.
Okay. The
Mandian says significance of new
military bases along Siliguri. You mean
Bangladeshi bases or Indian bases? Um
if if the Bangladeshes are putting up
new bases, let them do it. Let them do
it. Who cares? Makes no difference. If
we are putting up new bases, well, good.
Vimir Singh, good to see you, sir.
Thoughts about boxing dying as a sport?
No. Ali or Frasier or listen today? What
do you think about influencer boxing?
Was it Jake or was it Logan?
Jake Paul or Log. Who was it? Jake Paul.
Yeah, it's Jake Paul, right? He
he fought Anthony Joshua. It was not a
very serious fight as I I just saw like
a three minute highlight highlights
reel. It was not a really serious fight
and it wasn't thrilling. It wasn't
exciting. Yeah, you're you're right.
There's no Muhammad Ali. There's no
Frraasier. There's no Lon. There's no
George Foreman. There's no Mike Tyson.
They've all retired. Um
yeah, it's kind of kind of stagnating,
kind of dying. It's it's sad. Uh people
are now these days more enamored with
MMA, you know, mixed martial arts. Um
which obviously is a more allround
discipline, isn't it?
And obviously MMA does use boxing
skills. So I think it's it's sad that
boxing is declining. There are no great,
you know, iconic fighters anymore today.
It's sad to see that. The last great
iconic fighter, the great the last great
fighter I saw was was obviously Mike
Tyson with his left hook. And you've had
some good fighters. You had the
uh who were those Ukrainian guys, two
brothers, they used to fight, not
Shepchinko, Shvchenko is a footballer.
Um and recently you had the other Tyson,
right?
um the gypsy ties him who was an
entertaining guy,
but yeah, it's not no longer exciting
anymore, which is sad. Which is sad.
Truly sad. Boxing is a great sport. Not
for everyone, not for good for watching
for most people. It it can damage your
brain, but yeah, it's sad that this
great sport is kind of declining now.
Vsvs says, "Namaste." Well, all right.
[laughter]
All right. Arian K says thoughts on
advant and trashism. Look, I am not um
I'm no expert in these in these matters.
My thoughts are not that relevant. You
ask me my thoughts about
about some element of physics some or
something like that it may be more
relevant. I am not an expert in these
matters.
So yeah,
VSVS says, "Question by Ocean Gupta.
What if we aren't real humans but
biological AI?" Like a higher
consciousness built this universe as a
sim or a simulation. You know, our DNA
is just the code that they wrote to see
if we'd ever realize we in a game.
That's possible. That's the simulation
hypothesis. This is one of the scenarios
that is part of what we call the
simulation hypothesis. The simulation
hypothesis is that you know
maybe somebody
some some higher civilization
created a simulation of a world inside a
computer. So when we play you know
PlayStation games or Xbox games
there's a world that that we are playing
in right the world is on the screen and
the character or whatever we're
controlling is immersed in that world
and the world is simulated inside the
computer's uh inside inside the computer
right so maybe we are inside a
three-dimensional fourdimensional
simulation created by higher dimensional
beings
you
And maybe we don't realize that
it's something I have been thinking
about for a very very long time without
even realizing I was talking thinking
about a simulation hypothesis. When I
was a little kid, I used to wonder if
the world really is what it is. If I
quickly look back, will I actually see
the real world or will will something
suddenly pop into existence a little
just a frame too late?
I used to wonder when I was a little
kid. I was obviously wondering about the
simulation hypothesis back then. So it's
it's possible it it kind of can explain
the way the world is. Uh will we ever
ever realize or can we ever devise a
test that can determine whether we are
actually in a simulation or not? I'm not
sure. That's something that should be
looked into. Is there a way to devise
some kind of way of testing determining
whether we are inside a simulation or
not?
But yeah, what if Yeah, it it's
certainly
possible that we may be in a simulation.
Okay. Krishnant Boroy says, "What's
going to happen in the Ukraine Russia
war?
The Ukraine Russia war will end with the
partition of Ukraine whenever it ends.
Will it end in 3 months? Will it end in
3 years? I don't know. Most likely it
will end
hopefully by the end of 2026. hopefully
before that depending on how Trump and
Putin are able to get things done. It
the onus is on Trump not on both
actually the onus is on Trump. So what's
going to happen eventually the the
nation of Ukraine will be partitioned
the eastern half will go to Russia
or eastern portion not half or quarter
or third or whatever will go to Russia.
The rest will remain as rump Ukraine.
That's what's going to happen. You
Russia is going to achieve its
military and political objectives.
Bijuya says, "Does
do substances like cocaine and marijuana
actually really increase creativity?
Once Stephen King said he wrote his best
novels like it, Cuyo, the stand while
consuming these substances,
I don't know.
It is alleged that cocaine makes you
more alert or something and
and it is said that marijuana is kind of
a depressant which means it makes you
slow and dull. I don't really know which
is which.
I suppose people who take cocaine are
more hyperactive and people who take
marijuana are more lethargic. That's the
impression I get or I've got.
Um, but does it increase
creativity?
I don't really know. These are different
kinds of stimulants and they affect your
the way your brain works. Does it does
one of these things make you more
creative? I don't really know. I I'm the
wrong person to ask this questions. Uh,
if Stephen King said that he did he
consumed these substances and did great
work, well, good for him. But I would
not recommend any of us do that. Okay.
[laughter]
Okay. UMXG lol haha says why does how
does VSVS come up with so many
questions? I think VSVS is doing
tremendous social service by by taking
questions from
u the viewers who are maybe students or
young people who can't take super chats
and he is taking super chats on their
behalf. Maybe that's how he's coming up.
with so many questions. So VSVS and VSPS
has also donated many memberships of the
channel and Ankita G also has done that
and some other people have also done
that. So I am really grateful to all of
you my viewers and to VSVS also
definitely specifically for being so
kind to everyone who's watching. Thank
you.
Vir Kamat says if is the widespread
protein deficiency caused by the carb
heavy extremist vegetarian influence
dietary habits responsible for poor
Olympic or sports performance? No.
No.
Um
the protein deficiency that most Indians
suffer from it's because starvation diet
has become our tradition.
The past 300 or so years before 1947,
India was under brutal genocidal British
occupation. The British engineered
hundreds of artificial famines during
which Indians had to rely on a
starvation diet.
What is starvation diet? You have to
rely on cooking things that that you can
store for a very very long time like
pulses and things like that.
And you rely on
on on carbohydrate staples like rice
etc.
And that became so you have rice you
have dal
then from rice you can make idlies and
dosas and stuff. So everything became
became carb heavy and now it's become
part of a tradition. We think it's our
it's our heritage. It's our it's our
culture. It's our tradition. That's what
we eat. But if [snorts] you read ancient
texts like the manasulasa etc. you will
see there was there was so much variety
of the kind of protein sources we ate we
we consumed so that's why
Indians today have this tremendous
protein deficiency and carb heavy diets
but is that it's not responsible for
poor sports performance the reason why
we have poor performance in sports is
because we are a lowinccome nation
sports is a luxury for most Indians do
you understand because most Indians
barely have enough money to live from
day to day
even today.
That's the reason why we have poor
sports performance. We are not a high
income nation
and also because see even poor nations
can produce great athletes if the
government allocates specific funding
for sports but in India it's like
so that's why we have poor sports
performance not because of the diet.
When you are a sports person, your diet
automatically changes. Otherwise, you
don't you can't perform. So that's the
problem.
Min reminds me, thank you for the
reminder. You are going to upload
compilation of of your book reviews. I
shall do that. Thank you for the
reminder. I have been a little lax in
that matter, but yes, I shall do it.
Thank you so much, Maktlean G, for the
reminder.
Okay. Push Suri has become a new member.
Thank you very much, Push. Welcome to
the membership. Really appreciate it.
Godliness says from farm laws and CAA
agitation to Bangladesh and Qatar why do
we look so helpless all the time till
when do we need to show this strategic
restraint this government can't even
manage manage the online propaganda
once again let me remind you like I have
said so many times I have pointed out a
fact
what is this fact that when it comes to
Western Europe
the major power there is the United
States. It's not Germany. It's not
France. The major power in Western
Europe is the United States.
What is the major power in the Indian
subcontinent? Is it India? No, it's the
United States.
The sooner we start realizing this, the
the sooner we will start understanding
what's happening and why why the
government of India has certain policies
that frustrate us.
It's because the major power in the
Indian subcontinent is also the United
States even though it is physically not
here because it has proxies.
It has proxies to which it has probably
given nuclear weapons.
And when it comes to nations in like
like Qatar, they are also US proxies.
Everything is coordinated.
And when you have a nation like the US
which is like
which is like 20 times more powerful
than India, the government of India has
to take a step back
for the for the interest of the nation.
So that's how it is. So how long will we
have to show this strategic interest a
restraint at least 20 more years?
You will not like this answer but it is
a fact. Minimum 20 more years we'll have
to like Deng Shaoping said b our time
and grow.
Vipul Pawar says is physics limited by
data or by ideas?
H
is physics limited by data or by ideas?
So first of all let's define what is
physics. Physics is the laws of the
universe. laws that govern the universe.
The universe you will see it is full of
regularities and patterns and we encode
or represent these regularities and
patterns using the ma language of
mathematics and we use that to try and
define
generalizations
which are what we call the laws of
physics. the law of gravitation, general
relativity, quantum mechanics, quantum
field theory, the law of
electromagnetism,
um electro theory, the the standard
model of physics, all of these things,
these are our best mathematical
representations of the regularities and
patterns in the universe. So what limits
our understanding of physics? Is it
data? To some extent, it is data. We
don't know what lies beyond the
observable universe. There is a posity
of data. The data is not available. So
yes, we don't know the true shape of the
universe or the size of the of the
universe. So that understanding of
physics is limited by data, lack of
data, ideas. Certainly we are out of
ideas right now as to
about when we try to to figure out what
is dark matter or dark energy. We are
kind of currently out of ideas. We will
need somebody to make a breakthrough
somewhere. So there's a limitation by
ideas also. There is a third limitation
that we don't acknowledge. It is the
limitation of the human intelligence. It
is possible the universe is too complex
for
monkeys to understand. We are after all
monkeys, aren't we? We are apes. Maybe
the universe is way too complex for
simple apes like us to understand. So
what is the highest IQ that's possible
for human beings? Um above 120 you're
intelligent IQ. above 150 IQ, you are a
genius. I think the highest human IQ
possible may be around 200, 220 or
something. But what if you need an IQ of
1,000 to actually understand the
universe? So there's a limitation there.
Limitation of human intelligence. So
what are the limitations? Data, ideas,
and human intelligence.
Godliness says we already face drought,
deforestation, decreasing water levels
in rivers and illegal mining. Now this
new cancer giving problem of EQI. Do we
even have the natural resources to be a
developed states state?
Look, AQI issue is about pollution.
Some of the
and and in northern India we have very
poor AQI during the winters. We know
that, right? Tremendous amount of smoke
and pollutants in the air. When you fly
over northern India, you can see the
smog and the haze and it's frightening.
What's the reason for this? Well, we are
a developing nation.
We are we have to use energy to develop
the energy. Most of it comes from
burning coal. When you burn coal, it's
going to send up all these smoke in the
air. We have so many vehicles. The
vehicles produce exhaust that also adds
that there is a major component of the
smoke in the atmosphere. And then you
have all the burning of the
what fields at the end of the harvest
season or whatever that also adds to a
lot of the smoke. So a lot of this is
then there's the the dust that comes out
of the tar desert which is a major cause
of the dustiness of the Indian
subcontinent. So all these factors add
up. Some of these factors can be dealt
with. Some of these are natural but
eventually as we develop more we should
be able to tackle this. That's the whole
thing. VSVS says in order to be a tank
you have to wear a tank top. Chab bean
Gita 1287.
I [snorts] I probably am not intelligent
enough to understand this. Maybe it
reads an IQ of one/3 of of of
maybe above 200.
[laughter]
Okay.
Uh Gahul effect says Hyderabad
government has imposed a second language
as Telugu only in sidelining Hindi which
resulted in protest by Hindi belt
immigrants. What are my thoughts? I have
no thoughts about this. I don't discuss
Indian
internal politics. So I will desist from
airing my thoughts over here and I'm not
aware of this issue anyway.
Okay. Biohomi says justice for SSR,
justice for Disha
and so on. Okay, if you say so, sir. All
right. Uh SK says thank you so much,
sir. Well, thank you so much. You too.
Thank you for your contribution. Thank
you so much.
K Christian Bordoy says, "Russia Ukraine
war ends. Putin said EU leaders are
pigs."
Um, has the war ended really?
Let me see.
Ukraine war. Has it ended?
Um, not sure if it's ended,
but anyway. Um, I'm not sure what Putin
has said, but all right. [laughter]
Uh
PLTP P R E LTP says, "Why is the US
pushing for social credit and
surveillance system? Why India loses a
propaganda war while other countries
succeed?
Is the US pushing for social credit and
surveillance?" So surveillance is all
over the place. The West is a police
state. Every Western nation is a police
state and a surveillance state. It's
been that way for a very, very long
time.
We people just don't realize that people
don't notice. People are sheep, right?
People don't notice. It's always been
that that way since the 20th century.
And the better the technology gets, the
more surveillance is going to be all
pervasive. So yeah, because they don't
trust their citizens. [laughter]
Um yeah, social credit, I am not sure
about social credit in the US, but yeah,
surveillance, state, social credit, it
all goes hand in hand. It's all about
control, control, control, control
everybody. So the west is not truly
democratic. It's only masquerades as a
democracy. It's it's it's an autocracy
actually very autocratic. But yeah, as
long as you operate within the
parameters of the autocracy, you will be
given high high quality living standards
and so on. So that's why the west is
seems to be great. Uh why does India
lose propaganda wars while other
countries succeed?
Look, the west is the master of
propaganda. The west has decided now
that India must be contained. The west
controls the media. The west controls
all the social media platforms and if
they control it they will you will
always lose. You will always lose.
That's why India loses. India doesn't
have its own media and its own social
media platforms. India has media but
they they puppet the they they parrot
the west. Not a single Indian journalist
that I am aware of has original thinking
when it comes to geopolitics.
Everybody's now a geopolitics expert.
All the news readers are now considered
to be geopolitical experts. None of them
has any original thoughts.
So that's why we lose the propaganda
war. When our own media amplifies
western narratives and anti-India
narratives, we don't have any any BBC or
CNN of our own. So then what do you
expect? We will lose every every
propaganda war. UMXG says when will you
develop your colonel? I don't think I
will ever develop a colonel. I don't
have the time to do that. And uh my my
software skills are super rusty now. I
haven't used those for a long time. Uh
should I develop a kernel?
That's that's a big project that takes
time.
H
interesting.
Let me think about it.
It certainly will be valuable.
Okay. Um thank you for the suggestion. I
I'll seriously consider that.
Bijua says with due respect according to
my observation
communists are stupid so socialist
socialists of some brain but still don't
have vision my views what are my views
look um
[laughter]
what are my views look um even
reasonably intelligent people become
communist right
I would say communism is a
is actually a brilliant
tool.
It's what what is the objective of
communism? I'll I'll explain what is the
purpose of communism.
The purpose of communism,
communism is a socopolitical toolkit.
Okay? Communism is a socopolitical
toolkit. And the purpose of communism
is to acquire and retain political power
and put that in the hands of a of a very
small number of people.
So how this is done is by recruiting
food soldiers who are told that you have
been oppressed for generations and these
are your oppressors. Go kill them.
That's a communist revolution.
And then when they start following you
and do all this, you acquire the power.
So communist leaders are typically super
charismatic people and they understand
how to control power. That's what
communism is. So the foot soldiers who
are who become enchanted with the the
ideology they typically are average
intelligence people and so on. So that's
my views about communis communism. Uh,
Rashad says, "Have you seen the new
Avatar Fire and Ash movie?" I haven't
seen it. I I saw the first movie back in
2009. It was a very interesting
experience, you know, 3D uh 3D was new
at the time and the movie was decent.
Uh, the second movie was kind of uh
visually stunning. The story was boring.
Third movie, I don't know. I don't know.
Maybe I'll see it, maybe I won't, but I
haven't seen it yet. Swami says, "Thank
you so much watching since April 2022.
Learn more than school." Thank you so
much. That's the nicest thing you could
say about me. Um, yeah. Um, that's
that's the reason I do it. Hopefully,
you all learn something or at least
learn how to think differently, learn
learn how to question. So, thank you so
much, Somi. Thank you so much.
Manov Patil says, "I'm 25 and I am in
the US on a student visa. I'm returning
to India in June 2025
or 26. Okay, you're returning to India
in June. I'm unable to get a job here in
the US and I've started doubting myself.
How to overcome this feeling of being a
failure and start all over again?
See, you have to remind yourself that
getting a job is not entirely in your
hands.
There are certain things, there are
certain outcomes in life [clears throat]
that are not entirely in your control.
What things are in your control?
What's in your control is how
hard and how well you study and how well
you perform in exams as a student,
right? As a student, that's that's what
you can control. So you can control your
schedule, your routine, your study
habits,
your discipline, all those things you
can control and that's the best you can
do. So once you do all that, you study
really hard, you've you've done
everything, then you have to perform
well in an exam and that performance is
no longer in your hands. You may write
all the answers correctly etc. But it
depends on how your teacher or professor
will evaluate that and that's going to
be up to that person and they may have
biases or not. So now it's not no longer
in your hands. Of course, if you perform
tremendously well, then it's really hard
to give you poor scores and all, but you
may still not get the scores you
deserve. So that's not in your hands.
And then if you study really well, you
know everything, but your professor
grades you
lower than what you deserve, then is
that a failure on your part? It's not,
right? It's not. It was not in your
control completely. Once again, when it
comes to getting a job, well, if you're
a job seeker and you send your resume,
etc., and you you may prepare really
well for interviews, etc. But if
the company where you're applying has
certain criteria that you don't meet,
then that's not in your control. Once
again, there may be hidden criteria too
that you're not aware of. Right? So, my
point is that should not make you doubt
yourself. There are things you can't
control.
There are outcomes you can't control.
So you overcome the feeling of being a
failure
um by first of all understanding this
that if you don't get a job, it doesn't
mean you are you are a failure. It means
that those people they wanted something
else,
right?
And to completely overcome the feeling
of being a failure, you have to succeed
in something at some point in time. And
the sooner you do it, the the better it
is for you. Um, so how do you succeed?
You apply to multiple companies. Maybe
there's a strike rate, you know, of
maybe 4%. Let's say hypothetically. So
if you apply to four to 100 companies,
you will succeed get through in four.
But if you apply to only four companies,
there's a high possibility you won't get
a single single job. So you have to
maximize your your chances for success
by understanding the odds, understanding
the percentages and know you you know
and and adjusting accordingly.
So think about this logically.
Keep your emotions out of it. It's it's
not easy. I know that. But learn to
dissociate your emo emotions from your
logical thinking and understand that
this is not entirely in your hands. So
this is this doesn't mean you're a
failure. All right. So uh Manov, I wish
you the best. Do well. I hope you
succeed at the earliest and and do your
best for that. Thank you. Vsvs says, "I
wish Ritwick my man would send his UPI
ID. He really deserves a treat from our
side for what he has done." Jes.
[laughter]
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I mean truly proud of
Ryik. [laughter]
Very very very
courageous young man indeed.
Kiki Susan says for science. Thank you
so much sir. Thank you so much. For
science indeed appreciate it very much
Susant. Thank you.
Sena says did you see Jawad Daktar
versus Miy debate on atheism versus
theist? No
this matter doesn't interest me at all.
Atheist versus theist and the debate
doesn't interest me. So I agree that
science is very different from mythology
and religion and should be kept
different. Yeah, science is totally
different from these things. Um, there
are all these debates which are I'm sure
very interesting but
my interests are elsewhere. I personally
am not into these debates. So, and and
you know what I am interest I am
interested in the truth about the
universe about the world. I'm not
interested in who wins a debate based on
how well they answer questions and how
well they outwit the other person in a
in verbal jousting. That doesn't that's
not something that interests me
specifically. I'm sure it's interesting
to a lot of people but not for me. So I
haven't seen this and uh
yeah that's what I'll say. [laughter] Uh
Abhir Sarkkar says how do you think the
perfect partition of India should have
been both geographically and in
managerial terms in 1947 if inevitable.
I was if I had been there I would have
been completely against partition.
[clears throat] I would have insisted no
partition. We have issues religious
issues whatever we will deal with them
internally.
That's what I would have said.
Um there is no perfect partition of
India.
Indian territory should never have been
given up.
So
yeah that's that's that's how I see it.
There are many people who will disagree
with me. There are people with who will
say that if we had not partitioned
India, then maybe 40% of India would
have been um Muslim. Let's say that's
what some people say.
Well, what's the Muslim population
percentage of India today?
We I don't know when was the last census
2011. Why hasn't the census happened
recently? I mean co is done now, right?
Yeah. So anyway, my point is we are
anyway living with our Islamic citizens,
right?
As long as there is strong leadership
and strong law and order, there'll be no
issues.
India should never have been partitioned
is is how I see it. I would not have
agreed to a partition ever. Vssvs says,
"Sir, was Freud an intellectual s
turning everything into mom and dad and
siblings?" I don't know.
I
Yeah, Freudian theory is all weirdness,
right? Everything is mom and dad and
siblings and Yeah. So I Yeah. So I
haven't really studied Freud in detail.
I'm aware of the contours of his
theories and all. Uh was he an
intellectual simp? I'm not sure. Look,
his theories are outdated and
unscientific actually. Yeah. But a lot
of people still put a lot of weight in
in in into Freudian analysis and stuff
which is actually unscientific and
um yeah was he an intellectual s?
He was not an intellectual. What is a s
by the way? Let's let's Google the
definition of simp
definition.
A silly or foolish person. Simpleton.
Okay. A simpleton. Intellectual
simpleton.
I think he was not an intellectual
simpleton. He was pretty profound
intellectually, I'm sure. But his
theories were wrong. Yeah.
VVS says, why do planets get ejected
from the solar system from from solar
systems? Because of gravitational
dynamics and mechanics.
Yeah.
uh see a to to condense it down to the
very fundamentals and basics.
A planet gets ejected from a solar
system when it acquires a velocity that
exceeds the escape velocity of its
parent star of its host star. Okay,
that's when a planet gets ejected from a
solar system and that happens
through gravitational dynamics.
Okay. Arnav
Arnav says, "Thoughts on the moon
landing? Did it really happen?" My
thoughts are that it really did happen.
And I've explained this in detail in the
past many times. See, when the US, we
know the US spent
a significant portion of its federal
budget like I don't know 5 6% I don't
know big big chunk of its federal budget
for several years on NASA. We know that
they built all these gigantic launch
facilities. They trained all these
astronauts. They built all the rockets,
massive rockets. We know they launched
rockets.
So, they may as well put people there
and send them to the moon, right? So, I
believe that they actually did uh do the
moon landings. Okay. Um [clears throat]
Arin says, "Plan on making videos
explaining physics with AI." I haven't
such plans yet. Physics with AI. You
know,
I don't I not I'm not a big fan of AI
videos, videos that use AI. It just
looks fake.
And when I read
text that is written with AI, I can
immediately tell if it's written by AI.
You can tell. So, I'm not a big fan of
using AI in creative work. I'm not a big
fan of that. So, if I do make videos
explaining physics, I will not use AI in
that. I promise you that much at least.
Uh VSVS says question by puken cosine.
Is it wrong to have kids since it
imposes unnecessary suffering on the
person being born and giving birth?
Absolutely not. Absolutely not. It is
not wrong to have kids. It is right to
have kids.
Everybody uners under undergo suffering
at some point in life. But life gives
you a lot of pleasure, a lot of joy as
well, lot of meaning. You can create
things. You can make the world better
also. Don't can't you?
You don't you should not look at the
world only from a negative perspective.
There is a lot of happiness and
positivity in life. Of course, there is
some suffering sometimes.
Why would you expect that the child will
only have suffering? Raise the child
right.
Give the child everything he or she
needs to succeed and then let the gods
decide what happens.
There'll be good, they'll be bad. That
is life. But it's not all suffering.
It's not that way. Please, let's not be
negative. All right.
Sah Dang has become a new member. Thank
you very much, Sah. Welcome to the
membership. Thank you so much for
becoming a member. I really appreciate
it. Thank you.
VSVS says, "Question by Pax Shield. How
fast does two bowling ball need to
travel towards each other and their
collision creates a black hole and how
massive will that black hole be?" Um,
how fast if you collide two objects
fast enough,
could they? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So,
definitely. Um, how fast will that have
to be? Well, for that I'll have to do
some calculations.
I can't just tell you right now like
this. I'll have to put pen on paper,
work out this thing.
Don't have an answer immediately for
you. I'll actually have to work work it
out. Pen on paper. So, yeah.
How about I
Okay, I'll take a screenshot of this
question and in the next live stream,
how about I answer this question? Yeah.
Okay. I'm I'm right now taking a
screenshot
of this question and I shall now save it
to a folder.
One second. One second. One second.
Okay. I shall now save it and in the
next live stream
I shall answer your question after
working it out after doing the the the
calculations. All right. I'll do that.
VSPS says Jes to you sir and to
everybody else.
Question by Ocean Gupta. Does our
0.0035%
visual wind window render our scientific
understanding a narrow provincial
delusion?
0.0035%
visual window. What is that?
I'm not sure what you're referring to.
Let me Google if that makes sense. 0.35%
visual
window.
Okay.
The tiny portion of the entire
electromagnetic spectrum that the human
eye can perceive. Okay. That's what
you're talking about talking about.
Visible light.
Okay. So, we can perceive a very tiny
sliver of the electromagnetic spectrum.
That's what you're talking about. Okay.
Does that render our entire scientific
understanding a narrow provincial
delusion? Absolutely not. Because in in
in today's day and age, we don't rely on
site to make observations. We have
instruments that capture electromagnetic
radiation for us.
We can detect ultraviolet rays,
ultraviolet light, ultraviolet photons.
We can detect infrared photons.
We can detect photons that are very near
absolute zero. What is the temperature
of CMBBR or cosmic microwave background
radiation? What's what's the what's the
energy? It's about 2.5 Kelvin, right?
2.7 Kelvin. Uh CMBR temperature. CMBBR
energy.
Energy. Uh temperature. Come on.
Yeah. 2.7 Kelvin.
Okay. A 3 MBR photon wavelength.
Yeah. What's the wavelength? Equivalent
wavelength. It's about 1.9 mm. We can't
see those photons. No way we can see
those photons. But we know they exist.
We can create detailed maps of the CMBBR
in the universe. Let's see. Okay. CNBR
map.
There we have it. How do we know this?
We can't see this.
They can we can't detect these photons
through our I mean
our retina can
no it can't [laughter]
we can't detect those photons visually
but we have made superdetailed maps of
the distribution of these photons so the
visual window has no effect anymore in
today's day and age on our scientific
understanding
vss says a question by bj
Baskar how V king restricted Ikbaku clan
Bara and in the shift to Nmada river
only.
Um
yeah uh
can't recall right now.
Yeah I can't recall right now. Sorry
sorry sorry. Um VSVS says simp is
someone who can be a servant to get a g
girlfriend. Girlfriend is it.
Oh okay that way.
All right. Okay. [laughter]
Uh Synica says tell me three books
everyone should read and also any book
how to study grasp and keep the stuff in
your brain. Lastly I think you were a
Indian we all going people needed. Thank
you for being you. Thank you so much.
Thank you so much. Um, three books
everyone should read. Ah, everyone
should read. Everyone,
three books everyone should read. These
questions always stump me
because I've read so many books. I can't
even remember the names of the books.
And if you ask me to just recommend
three of them
[sighs]
and that two for everybody
um
[laughter]
I don't know I'll say read the Bhagat
Gita the Raman and the Mahabharat
[laughter]
maybe that's the right answer maybe.
Obviously it doesn't cover everything
but no book covers everything. So okay,
read these three. [laughter] Anyway,
thank you so much. Thank you so much. Uh
UMX
G Laha says in Elon Musk's company de
developers were asked how many lines of
code they wrote and if it wasn't enough
they were terminated. Linus
such sort of metrics anyone who believes
that doesn't deserve to work in
technology thoughts. See, Elon Musk's
company developers were asked how many
lines of code they wrote and then the
code was evaluated for quality.
It's not like if you don't write 3,000
lines of code every day, you are
terminated. No. You have to write a
certain amount of code every week, but
then the quality also matters. So, it
was not merely quantity. You can write
20,000 lines of code in a week, but if
it is all garbage, then what's the
point? So it's not just quantity, it's
also quality. Elon Musk is not crazy.
He's not stupid. He has very high
expectations
from his employees. He is not an easy
boss. You think he will achieve all the
things he has achieved by being a very
nice, gentle, pampering boss. No,
absolutely not. He's ruthless.
If you want to achieve his level of
success, you have to be like that.
That's just the way it is. So I have I
am kind of aware of how Elon Musk has
done things. I've read a couple of his
biographies.
Uh I've I've read the biography by by by
by by Walt Isaxon and there's another
biography of his that came out before
that I also read. So I'm kind of aware
of how he operates and well you may like
it or dislike it but it gets gets things
done. So it is what it is. Okay. VPS Jam
to you sir. Thank you Jesam. VPS once
again says question by real painter
excuse me.
[clears throat] Um why did you say last
time it's too late to marry at the age
of 30. Look it's not too late to marry
even at the age of 70 if it if it works
for you. My point is the earlier you
have children the better it is for you
and the children also.
But I know that in the present day and
age you will not have enough money
potentially at the age of 23 to be able
to sustain a spouse and eventually
children. I know the Indian economy and
this current system is such that it's
very hard to do that but in an ideal
world you should get married at early as
as early as possible and have children
before you're 25. In an ideal world
under ideal circumstances but it's not
too late. I have not said it's too late
to marry by 30. Why did I say that?
I said ideally you should marry as early
as possible. Not at the age of seven
[laughter] when it is legally allowed to
marry.
That's what I've said. It's not too late
to marry even at the age of 70 if it if
if that's if it makes you happy. But you
won't be able to have kids then. But
whatever whatever works for you.
Okay. VSVS says
question by Numad Duni. How to have
understanding of physics? I'm sure you
learned this long ago but you still
remember and you us tell us road map
about physics. Thank you. And cool
hairstyle. Thank you for my Yeah, cool
hairstyle. How do you re how do you
understand physics? Well, if you want to
learn physics, see, there's a difference
between understanding something and
learning it properly. Understanding, I
can explain to you what a black hole is
through words. So, you will understand
hopefully to some extent, but you won't
really understand why it is the way it
is. I can give you analogies and all
that metaphors.
That's how you typically do popular
physics. But if you want to actually
learn physics, you have to do it step by
step. You start with the mathematics.
Without mathematics, you won't be able
to learn physics.
properly. So you need a solid foundation
in mathematics.
Now it depends on what kind of physics
you want to learn. First you will learn
classical physics, Newtonian physics.
So for that you will need basic
arithmetic.
You will need algebra trigonometry.
You will obviously eventually need
calculus integral and differential
differential integral integral calculus
and differential and differential
equations. Eventually going further
ahead you will need linear algebra or
you will need matrices and vectors and
tensor analysis tensor calculus
eventually. So you need the mathematical
toolkit based on where what you are
studying in physics and then you have to
do it step by step. You start with the
very basic Newtonian physics and you
learn it step by step.
So that's kind of how you do it. A road
map it's it'll take time to explain but
that's how you do it. You build a solid
foundation and you then build one floor
at a time in the building. That's how we
do it.
Okay. Um, Sica says, "I don't like your
three suggestions." Then be specific
about what you asking me, right?
Book students and young people should
read to learn how to learn, study, and
learn how to think. Okay, now you are
being a little more specific.
If you ask me to recommend three books
for for everyone.
So book that students and young people
should read to learn how to learn. I
don't know any such book.
Study to learn study and learn how to
think.
Do I know any such book? See in case you
are thinking that I learned how to think
by reading books. It's not the case.
I have not learned how to think and how
to process information
by reading books. That is something that
I suppose has come with the package.
I have not had to study how to think.
Okay. What is the right way of thinking?
How to structure your thoughts? How to
learn things. I have not read any of
these books.
I don't think I know any book that will
teach you these things. Maybe such book
book books exist but I don't know these
books.
Uh nobody ever taught me uh ever ever
taught me how to think. No book I read
has taught me how to think and how to
learn.
So I don't know such books sir. I'm
really sorry but I don't know such
books.
If I'm able to think, if I know how to
learn, I suppose I discovered that by
myself or maybe I just was born knowing
that that.
So I'm really sorry but I don't know
such books. I'm I'm sure such books may
exist. Critical thinking book. Is there
any such books? Um I don't I don't know.
Sorry. VPS says Ram Ram Ram Ram Ram.
Indeed, sir. Ram Ram Ram. Indeed. BSPS
says you should do a meme review or
meetup. Meme review.
And meme review. That's an interesting
thought. Where do I get memes from?
I'll think about it. I'm sure there must
be some way of doing a meme review. Meme
review about about what about what's
happening in the world.
Um,
okay. I'll think about it. Meetup. Um,
yeah, we can possibly do meetups.
That's also something I'll I'll keep in
mind. Thank you.
Raj Putin says, "Please talk about Gupta
Empire in detail its extent."
Ah,
well that's a huge topic. I mean, it's
one of the greatest empires that we've
had.
Huge topic. If I want to talk about that
in detail, it'll take me several hours.
But look it it starts
um about fourth century fifth century
AD. The first king was called Gatk.
He was just a minor king in Bhagad
but which eventually gave us some of the
greatest emperors we've ever had. So
um Chandra Gupta the first Kumar Gupta
Samudra Gupta Scandra Gupta was the last
great emperor and yeah it was a great
period of prosperity etc in India extent
almost the entire subcontinent almost
the entire subcontinent even parts of
Bahalik Gandhar etc. So we've ventured
beyond Gandhar and captured Bahalik and
that sort of thing.
Yeah. Monish Sabwal last question for
the day says I have seen many people
saying that marriage is not good
anymore. Okay. That marriage is not good
anymore and they are showing many cases
from both genders. Also seeing people
vilifying both genders daily fears me of
marriage in the future. Look when you
have laws that are biased
against a certain gender. When you have,
see, when you have these things, when
marriage, when it is possible for people
to for one gender to make a huge amount
of money just by marrying for a year and
then claiming divorce, when you have
laws that are skewed and biased against
one gender, then we're going to have
these issues. So, it's not a problem
with our culture or civilization. It's a
pro problem with the colonial legal
system and the laws that we have today.
It's it's we are still colonized. We
it's like we are still under foreign
occupation.
So that's how it is today. Yeah. Today
it is it is difficult. It is more
dangerous to be married to some gold
digger. It's it's indeed a problem
today. We see so many cases among
celebrities, right? Some leg spin
bowler, some somebody
who know God knows who else. So that's
that's an issue. It is today. Yeah. It
is actually scary. If I was a young man
today, 22 years old, I would probably be
scared of getting married. Yeah.
Um,
so my what do you do in this situation?
You have to find the right person. You
to find the right either you get lucky
or you don't. Either you get lucky or
otherwise you get unlucky. You have to
find the right person. How do you find
the right person? Probably let your
parents find the right person for you.
Maybe they are more experienced.
I don't know. It's your choice. Uh VSVS
says you have a subreddit on Reddit.
Sarah Jam I am not aware of a subreddit
on Reddit. Maybe somebody created my
name. I'm not sure.
Abishek Kumar Moria says in next 50 100
years all Hindus will convert sir. I
hope not. I hope not. But the way things
are
it seems to be going in that direction
unfortunately.
Uh Sica says I did not mean to be rude.
No, no, no. for not being rude. It's
fine. It's fine. It's fine. I I do not
find what you said rude
and I understand that words are limited
here and that sort of thing. It's okay.
I I'm not angry or upset with you at
all. It's I and I I'm I'm sorry if I
sounded rude or angry. I don't mean to
be angry or anything. So, this will be
the last one for the day. I got my
question about books was too broad and
it was my mistake. I want answer about
my favorite three books. You know what?
I will
my favorite three books.
I have dozens of favorite books. I can't
boil it down to just three.
I can't
Maybe I'll make a
make a separate video about my top 50
favorite books or something. Maybe that
that makes sense because I have so many
interest. I've read so many books in so
many different domains. How can I
compare a book my three favorite books
with physics with my three favorite
books in something else? You can't,
right? Maybe I should make a separate
video about that. Yeah.
And Arian says, "Let him sleep, guys."
So, I would actually agree with Arian.
Please let me sleep now. It's been 4 and
a half hours. My god, [laughter]
four and a half hours. This was supposed
to be a two-our session, but you know
what? Thank you so much. You asked me so
many questions. I
It's a privilege. I keep like I keep
saying it's a privilege that people want
to ask me questions. So thank you so
much. I'm genuinely privileged that I
have you all as my audience. You ask me
all these questions. So yeah, I will end
it here. This is the last super chat
that I have. It is dealt with. Thank you
so much everybody. Ending the live
stream now.
Thank you everyone. I look forward to
seeing you all in the next live streams.
I wish you a good day, good night, good
morning, good evening where you are.
Take care, keep learning, keep asking
questions, keep raising your standards.
I'll see you very soon in the next live
stream. Good night from here. Bye-bye.